<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Every-dayes sacrifice Wherein are comprehended many comfortable prayers and meditations, very necessary for all Christians. Also, many comforts for the sicke which are afflicted by the sight of their sins and the terrour of death; written by D. M. Luther, a little before his end. With most true comforts out of holy Scripture of the knowledge we shall haue of one another in the world to come. Translated by, W.R.S.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 141 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114714</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849937</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19962)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1480:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Every-dayes sacrifice Wherein are comprehended many comfortable prayers and meditations, very necessary for all Christians. Also, many comforts for the sicke which are afflicted by the sight of their sins and the terrour of death; written by D. M. Luther, a little before his end. With most true comforts out of holy Scripture of the knowledge we shall haue of one another in the world to come. Translated by, W.R.S.</title>
                  <author>W. R. S., fl. 1624.</author>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 276 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Humfrey Lownes, for Iohn Parker, and are to be sold at his shopin Paules Church yard at the sign of the three Pigeons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Every dayes sacrifice, attributed to Martin Luther but probably not in fact by him.</note>
                  <note>The translator's initials are transposed only in this edition to: W.R.S.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Euery-daies sacrifice.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with separate dated title page: A comfort against the fear and terror of death, and the graue; being an exposition of Doctor Martin Luther, written a little before his end.</note>
                  <note>Register and pagination continuous.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; leaf M1 torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>EVERY-DAYES SACRIFICE.</p>
                  <p>Wherein are comprehended <hi>many comfortable Prayers and</hi> Meditations, very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ns.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALSO,</hi> Many comforts for the ſicke which are affliſted by the ſight of their ſins and the terrour of dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h; Written by D. M. Luther, <hi>a little before his end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With moſt true comforts out of holy Scripture of the knowledge we ſhall <hi>haue of one another in the world to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tranſlated by, <hi>W. R. S.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Humfrey Lownes,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Parker,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Paules Church yard at the ſign of the three Pigeons. 1624.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>The Tranſlator to <hi>the Reader.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) in his laſt great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation 1603. (amongſt a great multitude of others) to take to his mercy al my Children, to the great griefe and ſorrow of my heart, which cauſed me to remember the ſaying of
<pb facs="tcp:15111:3"/>our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt in his holy Goſpel: <hi>If theſe things bee done vnto a greene Tree, what ſhall bee done to a dry?</hi> And therefore it beſeemed mee, rather to prepare for my ſelfe, that I might bee ready when it pleaſed God to call mee, then to lament for them which are at reſt with Chriſt. All which conſidered, cauſed mee to reade ouer diuers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Bookes; and at laſt light vpon this, which as it appeareth in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this book, was firſt penned for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:15111:3"/>of one that was in great affliction by reaſon of ſickneſſe; who, beſides a great number of others, receiued great comfort of the ſame; for which cauſe it was firſt penned. The like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort hath it, by the goodneſſe of God, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in mee; which moued mee to vndertake the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing hereof in as plaine and fruitfull manner as I could, for the good of euery Chriſtian, without any borrowed phraſes. And therefore ſuch as it is, I commend to thy fauo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable acceptance, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:15111:4"/>God that it may work ſuch comfort in thee (and in all other that ſhall reade it) as it hath done in mee, for the glory of his holy name: vnto whoſe moſt mighty protection I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:4"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Exhortations to make the ſick <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of death.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E bee but ſtrangers and ſoiourners, as were all our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: our daies on earth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are but as a ſhadow, and there is no abiding.</p>
                     <p>The dayes of man are the daies of an hireling, yea wind and nothing.</p>
                     <p>We are made as duſt, and muſt return to duſt, as a leaf that is carried of the winde, dry ſtubble, and a garment that is moth-eaten.</p>
                     <p>Man is burthened with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15111:5"/>many calamities: he cometh vp, &amp; is cut down like a flour, and he lieth as it were a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: ſhort be his dayes, and the Lord hath appointed him his bands, which he ſhall not paſſe.</p>
                     <p>Where is there any man that liueth, and ſoeth not death?</p>
                     <p>Our daies paſſe away ſwiftly, and we are gone.</p>
                     <p>A man in his time is but as graſs, and floriſheth as a flour of the field: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> as ſoon as the winde goeth ouer it, it is gon, and the place thereof knowes it no more.</p>
                     <p>Man is like to a thing of nought: his daies paſſe away like a ſhadow.</p>
                     <p>Euery thing hath a time,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15111:5"/>yea, all that is vnder heauen, hath his conuenient ſeaſon. There is a time to bee borne, and a time to dy.</p>
                     <p>Death doth not forget him ſelf.</p>
                     <p>By one man, death entred into the world, and went ouer all men; and through one ſin of one man, all men are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto death.</p>
                     <p>All fleſh is as graſs, and all the glory of man is as the flower of graſſe.</p>
                     <p>Our life is euen as a vapor that appears for a little tune, and then vaniſheth away.</p>
                     <p>Héer haue we no continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing city, but wée ſeek one to come.</p>
                     <p>Whatſoeuer hath béen borne ſince the beginning of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15111:6"/>the world vnto this day hath been ſubiect vnto death: and whatſoeuer is yet aliue, or ſhall be born, muſt néeds die euery-while.</p>
                     <p>Whoſoeuer receiueth life, muſt alſo ſuffer death reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe.</p>
                     <p>On this condition cameſt thou into the world, that thou ſhouldſt leaue it again.</p>
                     <p>Thou haſt béen ſure of death, euer ſince thou waſt conceiued in thy mothers womb.</p>
                     <p>Whatſoeuer thou haſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ouer the firſt day of thy birth, is ſuperfluous and too much; and God hath ſuffred thee to liue long enough.</p>
                     <p>There is no remedy, but that thou muſt néeds die, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15111:6"/>no man can ſaue thee nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee: for, thou art duſt, and muſt bee turned into duſt again.</p>
                     <p>Think none other in thy minde, but that the end of thy life is comne.</p>
                     <p>This miſery geeth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euer thee: for, great and ſmall, rich and poor, yong, old, Lord, ſeruant, man, woman, and all men muſt take this iourney in hand.</p>
                     <p>This debt haſt thou owed a great while, and thou muſt néeds pay it; the ſooner the better.</p>
                     <p>If thou ſhouldſt be put to death or execution, with a hundred more beſides thy ſelfe, what ſhould it auaile thee, whether thou were the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15111:7"/>firſt or the laſt.</p>
                     <p>He that is firſt diſpatcht, is ſooneſt rid out of his pain.</p>
                     <p>Thou haſt full well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the hand of God, to die a worſe and a more ſudden death: wherefore thou art bound to thank him, that hee handleth thee ſo graciouſly.</p>
                     <p>This life is ſhort: childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood flowes away like water: youth and manhood are full of ſin and labour: age is full of infirmities, although not one among a thouſand doth attain to it.</p>
                     <p>This life is but a priſon, full of heauineſſe, calamity, bondage, incombrance, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, labour, trauailes, vnluſtineſſe, ſinne, diſeaſes, temptations, yea, 'tis nothing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15111:7"/>but a croſſe. From all which miſeries, death dooth deliuer vs.</p>
                     <p>The day of death is better than the day of birth.</p>
                     <p>In the day of birth, thou art put to cold, heat, hunger, thirſt, tediouſneſſe, ſinne and wretchedneſſe. In the day of death art thou deliuered from all bodily impediments.</p>
                     <p>Therefore doo <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> curſe not onely the day of birth, but alſo him that brought the meſſage to their father, that a child was born.</p>
                     <p>The bitterneſſe of death which is ſent thee, paſſeth all the paine that euer thou dibſt ſeele in all thy life: but it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth not long, and it is ſoon done.</p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15111:8"/>
                     <p>Through the grace &amp; help of GOD canſt thou wade through this danger, &amp; drink this cup.</p>
                     <p>Thou didſt neuer truely feel the paſſion of Chriſt in all thy life: wherefore now in the houre of death thou ſhalt patiently féel and taſte.</p>
                     <p>In caſe the diuell by force, for his laſt feat, would proue himſelf vpon thee; then bée thou ſure, that he is a might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe enemy, and is ouercome by Chriſt, and can gette no more at thy hand, but onely as much as thou feareſt him, and doubteſt in Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>If there happen vnto thée any fearfull temptation, giue thanks to God, that he hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee ſo gratiouſly: for,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15111:8"/>thou art worthy to haue a more grieuous puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>The wicked ſpirit which tempted Chriſt, wil not leaue thée vntempted: but hée can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preuaile againſt thée; for, he hath nought in Chriſt, nor in thée.</p>
                     <p>Many temptations ſhall aſſault thee, which thou muſt patiently ſuffer; thinking, that the Lord might iuſtly ſend thée greater temptations, which neuertheleſſe he leaues vndone of his meer mercy.</p>
                     <p>When thy conſcience doth lay before thée thy manifould ſins, and ſendeth thée to good works; then remember, that Chriſt hath paid for thy ſins vpon the Croſſe.</p>
                     <p>Let not vnprofitable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15111:9"/>thoughts trouble thee; as, If God would lengthen thy life, thou wouldſt think to become more holy, and more apt to die: for, although thou mightſt liue yet (which is vnpoſſible) an hundred yéers, thou canſt deſerue nothing with thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe before God.</p>
                     <p>Although all creatures were againſt thée, yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God himſelfe ſhould lay before thée his fearfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and terrible indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſhew himſelf none otherwiſe than as though he were thine enemy, &amp; although thou ſhouldſt ſee nothing but diuels about thee, yet care not for it, whatſoeuer thou feeleſt: ſhut the eyes of thy minde: take hold of faith, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15111:9"/>truſt in the Goſpell. There is no Diuell ſo ſtrong, that is able to ouerthrowe it. Truſt to God, and feare not. Caſt all thy care on the Lord, and hee will prouide and preſerue thee.</p>
                     <p>Hitherto thou haſt béen as dead, but now ſhalt thou firſt begin to liue: for, death is a do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of life, a beginning of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and a departing from ſin and pain.</p>
                     <p>Forſake the world, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue death (which is ſeat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee by the grace of God) willingly: for, it is thy owne, and muſt alſo ſerue thee for thy wealth.</p>
                     <p>This ſmart and paine is ordained for thee of God, and hee doth not chaſten thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15111:10"/>he hateth thée, but that hee may preſerue and receiue thée as his ſonne. Therefore faint not, ſéeing thou art cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>No maner of chaſtiſing for the preſent time ſeems to bée ioyous, but grieuous: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, afterward it bringeth the quiet fruit of righteouſnes vnto them which are therein exerciſed.</p>
                     <p>The afflictions of this life are not worthy of the glory which ſhall bee ſhewed vpon vs.</p>
                     <p>Tribulation, anguiſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, hunger, nakedneſſe, perill, ſword, death, life, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, rule, power, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, height, lowneſſe, neither any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15111:10"/>other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God.</p>
                     <p>If thou didſt truly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and conſider the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, falſhood, blaſphemy, and the Antichriſtian conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and life of this world, truely thou wouldſt not couet to liue any longer.</p>
                     <p>A thouſand liues (if it were poſſible) oughtſt thou to loſe, onely becauſe thou haſt heard and taſted the goſpell; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that thou haſt obtained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes through the bloud of Chriſt, and not through thine owne merits.</p>
                     <p>Thou haſt prayed daily, that it would pleaſe GOD to take thee out of this euill
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15111:11"/>world into his Kingdom, and that his will might be done. Wherefore, ſéeing hée will now, through his grace, bring thee into his Kingdome, thou oughtſt (as his ſon) willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gladly to obey, and to reioice with all thy heart, that thou, out of the diuels King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, out of this vallie of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and out of this wretched life, commeſt to thy Father, and all his Elect in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Paradiſe.</p>
                     <p>The Heathen, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding were without hope, did, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of the life to come, deſtroy themſelues: and ſhouldſt thou, béeing a Chriſtian, to whom ſo much comfort, hope, and euerlaſting life is promiſed, deſpaire in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15111:11"/>death, and deſire not to die with all thy heart?</p>
                     <p>The Iewes die merrily, which neuertheleſſe haue cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Chriſt, and are damned for euer: and ſhouldeſt not thou, being a Chriſtian man, be more earneſt and bolder to die; to whom ſuch ioy is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eie hath not ſéen, the eare hath not heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath entred into the hart of man? and wouldeſt thou now giue place to the miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and curſed Heathen and Iewes, in bodily dying?</p>
                     <p>The ſeruant is not aboue his Lord, nor yet the Diſciple aboue his Maſter. Chriſt thy Maſter and Lord ſuffered and died for thée: thou muſt alſo ſuffer and die.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15111:12"/>
                     <p>All they which are baptized to die, are baptized: thou art baptized, therfore art thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo baptized to dy.</p>
                     <p>For Gods ſake art thou killed, and art counted as a ſhéep appointed to bee ſlame. What were a ſlaughter ſhéep, if it were not ſlaine? or what were a Chriſtian man, if he ſhould not be aſſaulted, ſuffer, and die?</p>
                     <p>Faint not in this affliction, to which thou knoweſt thy ſelf to be conſtituted.</p>
                     <p>Now will Chriſt thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and Redéemer prooue whether thou wilt ſtand by him or no, whether thou wilt for his ſake valiantly abide death, and bee like vnto the ſhape of his paſſion, or not.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15111:12"/>Therefore ſuffer now as a good warrior of Ieſus Chriſt, and think not to be crowned, vnleſſe thou fight valiantly: for, if thou die with Chriſt, thou ſhalt alſo liue with him, thou ſhalt alſo triumph with him.</p>
                     <p>Unfaithfull and without honour is hee counted before the world, that giueth-ouer his holde in his dominions: &amp; ſhouldſt thou not bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out honour, if in the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of death thou ſhouldeſt ſhrink from Chriſt thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour?</p>
                     <p>Take vp thy Croſſe and death, and follow him.</p>
                     <p>Knoweſt thou not, with what great ioy and deſire all the Apoſtles and ſeruants of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15111:13"/>Chriſt haue ſhed their bloud for Chriſts ſake, and haue gon euen to meet death?</p>
                     <p>For Chriſts ſake haſt thou not yet ſuffred any ſpeciall thing. Therefore giue thy ſelf willingly and ioyfully vnto death, as a ſhéep, for Chriſts ſake.</p>
                     <p>God is by thée in thy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: he will pluck thée out of it, and bring thée to honor; and he is at thy right hand, that he may help thée.</p>
                     <p>Put now thy truſt in God, and thou ſhalt be holpen.</p>
                     <p>Bee of good comfort, and beſtowe thy ſtinking carcaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is but wormes-meat, vpon Chriſt thy Redeemer and Sauiour, and truſt onely to him and his holy Goſpell,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15111:13"/>which is the power of GOD to ſaluation to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
                     <p>Abide the Lord, and let thy heart take ſure hold.</p>
                     <p>Commit thy cauſe vnto the Lord, and truſt in him: hée ſhall order it well enough.</p>
                     <p>Be ſober and watch: for, thine aduerſary the diuell, as a roaring lyon, will go about thée, ſéeking how he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure thée; whom reſiſt, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the faith.</p>
                     <p>Ye wreſtle not againſt fleſh and bloud, but againſt rule, againſt power, and againſt worldly Rulers of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this world, againſt the ſpirits of wickednes, yea, againſt ſinne, death, hell, and the diuell. For this cauſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15111:14"/>behaue your ſelf as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian champion, and take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the armour of God, that ye may bee able to reſiſt in the euill day, and to ſtand perfect in all things. Stand therefore, and your loynes girt about with verity, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on them a breſt-plate of righteouſnes, and ſhod with ſhooes prepared by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of peace. Aboue all, take vnto you the ſhield of faith, wherewith yee may quench all the fiery darts of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. And take the helmet of ſaluation, and the ſwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d of the Spirit, which is the word of GOD. And pray al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in all manner of neceſſities.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15111:14"/>
                     <head>¶ A ſhort inſtruction of the confeſſion of ſinnes.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt, becauſe all mankind by the lawes of GOD: Secondly, and alſo out of the ſorrow of death, the cruell martyrdome and bitter death of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, by reaſon of our ſinnes which hee took vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: Thirdly, and alſo out of the fearefull examples of holy Scripture, how God alwaies puniſheth the vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant, which continue in their ſinnes, and are bound to confeſſe the ſame, if they will bee quit thereof, and die happily.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15111:15"/>
                     <p>Therefore ſhould we poor creatures, with the great fearefull miſeries and woes, wherein we (alas!) through ſinne are grieuouſly fallen, repaire vnto our deare God with hearty ſighing and wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping earneſtly call for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as the holy Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did alſo; <hi>Enter not into judgement with thy ſeruant, O Lord.</hi> And let vs take héed, that we blaunch not our ſins, as the Hypocrites and the Phariſes did, <hi>Luke</hi> chapter <hi>18.</hi> For, the Cherubins and Angelles of GOD, which are wholly holy, doo couer their faces and feet, that is to ſay, all their glory, works, and dooings, and will not bée prayſed; but doo ſing with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15111:15"/>their voice, their <hi>Gloria, la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Gloria in excelſis Dee;</hi> to the end that GOD the Lord onely may bée acknowledged for holy, honoured, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                     <p>But in ſuch confeſſion of ſur, let vs not créep into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as <hi>Adam</hi> did, <hi>Geneſis</hi> the third chapter, but call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God from the bottome of our hearts for grace and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe, through the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deſeruing of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, as <hi>ieremy</hi> the fourtéenth chapter: <hi>Lord, we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our wickedneſſe, and the miſdeeds of our fathers. For, we haue ſinned againſt thee: and the offenſes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee haue angred thee, are great. But, for thy names
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15111:16"/>ſake, let vs not bee brought to confuſion. Let not the throne of thy glory be moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Remember yet, and let not thy Couenant with vs ceaſe. Thou art yet the Lord our God, on whom wee hope: for, thou canſt do all this.</hi> So did <hi>Dauid</hi> pray in the <hi>25</hi> Pſalme; <hi>Remember not, O Lord, the ſinnes of my youth, nor my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions: but thinke vpon me according to thy mercy, for thy goodnes ſake.</hi> And in the two and thirtith Pſalm hee ſpeaketh very comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: <hi>I ſaid, I will confeſs my tranſgreſſions, and thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaueſt mee the wickednes of my ſinnes.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Daniel</hi> in his ninth chapter prayed,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15111:16"/>
                        <hi>Lord our God, &amp;c. we haue ſinned, &amp; haue alas bin wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. O Lord, for thy righte ouſnes ſake turne away thy wrath and anger for our ſins ſake, wee are blamed of all them that are rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about vs: and now, our Lord &amp; God, heare the prayers of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, &amp; his complaints, and behold with fauor thy holie place which is deſtroyed for the Lords ſake.</hi> So likewiſe ſhould euery Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelfe, &amp; beléeue with his heart, that hée for Chriſts ſake, through ſuch faithfull prayer, ſhall ſurely obtaine Gods grace and forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, as it is ſaid and promiſed to all the faithfull, <hi>Iohn <hi>16. Verily, Verily, I ſay
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15111:17"/>vnto you, whatſoeuer you deſire of the Father in my name he wil giue it you</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id <hi>Ieremy <hi>14</hi>
                        </hi> ſaith <hi>Thou art the Lord our God, and canſt and wiſt doe all this ſame, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Heere follow certain Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, how a man ſhould call to God for grace, and forgiueneſſe.</head>
                     <p>O Almighty and Euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieus and mercifull Father, I poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner acknowledge from my heart, and confeſſe it alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee with my mouth, that I am (alas) a great ſinner, conceuied, borne, and growne
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15111:17"/>vp in ſinne: and ſo haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times tranſgreſſed thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commandements, with evill, ſinfull, vncleane, and vnſeemely thoughts, wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>, and wicked deeds. All which I do repent from my very heart, and pray and deſire thee of thy Grace, O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, indue mee with the Grace, and forgiue me all my ſinnes, in the name of thy deare and onely Senne, my Lord and Samour Ieſus Chriſt, in whom thou haſt promiſed me comfort, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all my ſinnes. I comfort my ſelfe with this gracious promiſe, <hi>Iohn 6.</hi> where thy deare Sonne ſaith; <hi>Who eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Bloud;</hi> That is,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15111:18"/>Who beleeueth on mee, hath euerlaſting life, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day.</p>
                     <p>Such godly and gracious promiſes of thy Son, doe I truſt vnto and beleeue, and am certaine, that I, through ſuch ſaith, haue forgiuenes of my ſinnes: and ſhall bee a child of thy Kingdome, and remaine ſo for euermore, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>Another Prayer.</head>
                        <p>O Thou Almighty and Euerlaſting God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, maker of Heauen and Earth, and of all Creatures, I poore, miſerable and ſinfull creature, come héere before
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15111:18"/>thy diuine Maieſty, full of ſin and vnrighteouſneſſe, and fall downe at thy féet before thy glorious Maieſty: for I haue mightily offended thee my Lord and God, and ſinned againſt thy commandements and done againſt thy godly will.</p>
                        <p>But becauſe I cannot other wiſe bee quit and free from this my heauy burthen, but onely through thée my Lord and God: Therefore doe I now from my very heart complaine vnto thee my woe and miſery; and eſpecially what I haue at this preſent franed in, and haue accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed the ſame againſt thy godly will: beſides all other (alas) which I daily commit,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15111:19"/>with deceit, in ſhew and falſe heart, with negligence, euill luſts and otherwiſe: whether it bee with euill thoughts, words or workes, wittingly or vnwittingly, ſecretly or openly; whether it bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, or the loue of my neighbour: All which I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vnto thee, and confeſſe it alſo from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my heart; and pray thee, that through thy grace thou wilt graciouſly and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly forgiue mee all my ſinnes. Haue reſpect onely to the bitter death, Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and bloud-ſhedding of thy onely deare Sonne, in whom thou art pleaſed, who innocently died for mee poore ſinner. O my Lord and God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15111:19"/>looke vpon thy deare Sonne, and eſpecially on the great loue which hee ſhewed vnto vs poore ſinners, when hee went ſo patiently and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to death. O looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the great obedience which thy deare Sonne hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for our ſakes, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe vpon the er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>th, graue, and hell. O looke alſo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>on the great gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> to, wherewith thou haſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned thy Sonne, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> thou haſt made him Lord ouer all. For which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>our, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ee, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ou wouldſt graciouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>ue me this daies offence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into I, by temptation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>llen, with all my form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r ſames which I haue done
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15111:20"/>from my youth: For in ſinne was I conceiued, borne, and brought vp, and yet doe liue therein without ceaſing: So that ſinne hath gone through my whole bodie, marrow, and bones. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech thee moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly to remit and forgiue me all ſuch ſinnes, to caſt the ſame behind thée, and neuer thinke more on them, nor puniſh my body or ſoule, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this world, or the world to come: for thou art rich vnto all that call vpon thée. And becauſe thou wilt not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he turne from his wickednes and liue: therefore do I pray thee to giue me a good meaning to amend my
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15111:20"/>life, eſpecially in that thou haſt promiſed mee alſo, through thy deare Sonne, to giue mee whatſoeuer I aſke in his name.</p>
                        <p>Therefore do I pray thee through Chriſt, thou wouldſt forgiue mee all theſe my ſins, and poure thy holy Ghoſt into my heart, that I may conſtantly abide in a godly life. All which grant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee for thy deare Sonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſt, my Lord and Sauior, Amen,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15111:21"/>
                        <head>Another prayer to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Son of God, for grace, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> My deare Lord Ieſus Chriſt, I confeſſe vnto thee from the bottome of my heart, with great ſighing, that I am, alas, a poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, conceiued and home in ſinne and iniquity, to haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued wickedly againſt thee and thy holy Word, with vngodly and vnthankefull heart, for which I am hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorry.</p>
                        <p>But I am comfored in my heart, <hi>that thou wilt not the death of a ſinner,</hi> which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15111:21"/>thou haſt ſworne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with an oath: <hi>That thou wilt not be angry with me for euer,</hi> nor yet for euer puniſh mee. Thou doſt call and entice all them that are weary, oppreſſed, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſorrowfull bearts and conſciences, to thee and thy holy Word: and nameſt thy ſelfe <hi>A heauenly Phyſicion,</hi> which takeſt vpon thee our woes and miſeries (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee through ſinne are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len) and bringeſt to vs thy euerlaſting helpe and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by Preaching of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goſpell, wherewith wee may be holpen for euermore: vpon ſuch thy gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes come I to thee, and pray thee from the bottome
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15111:22"/>of my heart (O my Lord God and Sauiour) to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to me poore ſinner, like as thou haſt promiſed ſuch mercy, for the loue of thy owne grace &amp; merits: Amen, Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>The Lords Prayer contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a ſhort forme.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ABba,</hi> deare Father; wée thy vnworthy children call vpon thee in the name of thy beloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, through thy holy Ghoſt, vphold vs by thy holy Word, giue vs honeſt and true Teachers and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to diſtribute the ſame amongſt vs: Releaſe vs quickly out of the Diuels
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15111:22"/>kingdome; bring vs to thy Kingdoom of Grace, and to euerlaſting life: And giue vs thy holy Spirit, that wee, as the Angels of God, may liue holily, according to thy will and pleaſure. Nouriſh, bleſſe, and preſerue our houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, Wiues, Children, and Seruants, in this life: couer our treſpaſſes and of fences, and giue vs a louing heart, to forgiue all thoſe that haue offended vs. Let vs not conſent vnto ſinne, nor fall from thy onely Word of ſaluation, but keepe vs from the euill Fiend, and from all his deceites. Thou art a moſt mightie King, powerfull to rule; thou canſt, and wilt grant vs all theſe things:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15111:23"/>For which wee will giue thee thankes, and praiſe thee for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer (wherein the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Chriſtian Faith is ſimply contained) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a man may cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God for ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of his faith.</head>
                        <p>O Almightie and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, which art a Father of all grace and mercy, and a God of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. for vs poore ſinners, which I and all Chriſtians (through reuealing of thy Word) doe acknowledge and beleeue for certain, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15111:23"/>doe I land, honour, and praiſe thee, deare Father of heauen, for ſuch thy vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loue, wherewith thou haſt graciouſly had reſpect to vs thy enemies, tranſgreſſors of thy commandements, and damned creatures: Namely, in that thou haſt not ſpared thy onely Sonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who is equall with the God head, and with the holy Ghoſt: Eſpecially that thou haſt let him bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate for our ſinfull nature and doings, with our actuall miſdeeds: and howſoeuer we haue thereby deſerued, and into manifold horrible repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and finally to yeeld himſelfe to the ſhamefull death of the Croſſe. And ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15111:24"/>of pure fatherly loue, haſt ordained him a Lambe, to carry my ſinnes, and the ſins of the whole world vpon the Croſſe, and to be a perfect Oblation therefore, and doſt proffer, proclaime, and promiſe the ſame throughout the whole world, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt alſo the ſame to be belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, vpon paine of loſing euerlaſting ſaluation: for thereby, and by no other meanes, muſt it onely bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and impropriated to me, and to all the faithfull, and to bée our owne.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, deare Father, do I conſtantly beleeue, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the holy Goſpell, all this ſame, and doubt not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15111:24"/>thereof any thing at all, as I thy Childe am bound, and will doe, not reſpecting my vnworthineſſe. In Chriſt thy onely Sonne, are all my ſins, and all which beleeue, and boldly truſt vnto it, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently puniſhed, corrected, ſpent, and through his perfect obedient death of the Croſſe, all killed and taken away: And that I am, and alſo all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, through ſuch faith, planted in the Kingdome of thy deare Sonne (as the holy Scripture ſaith) by whom we haue redemption through his bloud: namely, remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
                        <p>I beleeue alſo verily, that in the death of Chriſt thy deare Sonne, my death is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15111:25"/>ouercome, that it ſhall neuer hurt mee nor conſume mee into damnation, (as the Scripture ſaith) Chriſt hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ed of death for all; hath taken into his power, and brought to lighten vntranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory life and being, through his Goſpell.</p>
                        <p>I beleeue alſo, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ell, which was done by thy deare Sonne, is deſtroyed and torne aſunder for mee and all faithfull; that the ſame cannot conſume or deuoure mee, nor any of the right beleeuers, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ll, where is thy victory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> And in another place; <hi>The gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt the right Beleeuers.</hi> And <hi>The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15111:25"/>Prince of this world is iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I beleeue alſo, that thy Commandements, with all the power thereof which they haue, haue no more right ouer mee, although I cannot abſolutely keepe them: For the Lord Chriſt thy deare Sonne hath through his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience perfectly kept the ſame for mee, and taken from them the right and intereſt which they had in mee: wherewith thou almighty, Euerlaſting, and Merc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>full God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, art ſatiſfied.</p>
                        <p>I beleeue alſo, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt thy deare Sonne, is a new life vnto mee, and to all faithfull, vnto euerlaſting life.</p>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15111:26"/>
                        <p>Finally, I beléeue alſo (as the Scripture ſaith) that hee is aſcended into Heauen, and hath taken rule on the right hand of his Father: and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth for me and al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that hencefoorth the Diuell and all his power is taken, muſt bee ſubiect, and lie at the feete of mee and all the Faithfull.</p>
                        <p>Therefore I pray thée, O Lord GOD, thou infinite Fountaine of all grace, that through the power &amp; work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Ghoſt, thou wilt giue mée ſuch faith and acknowledging this day and lawaies, to the end of my life.</p>
                        <p>And I pray thee alſo, my Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15111:26"/>art true and perfect GOD with the Father and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; foraſmuch as thou haſt put thy ſelfe vnder the tyranny of the Law, which (by reaſon of ſinne) it had towardes mee and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and haſt taken on thée my ſinne, Death, Hell, and damnation, which I by all reaſon, right, and rigour thereof ſhould haue borne; that thou wilt help to ſtill and pacifie theſe great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes betwéene GOD our heauenly Father and mee, eſpecially in my conſcience, which continually diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth mee, through the power of God, &amp; of the Holy Ghoſt, which thou haſt promiſed to ſend vs from the Father.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15111:27"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſo ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ek<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thou art the onely euer laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>vaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>parable truth: There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> do I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>edfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, by knowledge of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, that thou art to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                              <desc>••••••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o all Ecleeuers a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pneſt, a ſeat of Grace, and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uacate ſo thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father and I beleeue ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rily, (notwithſtanding that reaſon is aſtoniſhed thereat) that through no other Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion workes, or meanes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heauen or on Earth, our ſinnes, Death, Hell, and damnation, is ouercome and taken away and we at agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, but onely through
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15111:27"/>thee Ieſus Chriſt; whereon I will truſt, and alſo die thereon. Thereto helpe thou me, thou deare God, Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> LORD Ieſus Chriſt, which with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> one vnſeparable Eſſence, and a Fountaine of all Grace: I thanke and praiſe thee al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, that thou haſt alſo reuealed vnto mee thy grace for my better comfort, as thou haſt endued thy dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e Mother <hi>Mary,</hi> and alſo other Saints, with great grace, and wrought wonderfull workes in them. I pray thee therefore heartily to look vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15111:28"/>on mee with the eyes of thy mercy, as thou diddeſt looke vpon the euill doer, which was hanged vpon the Croſſe by thee, and diddeſt open his heart that hee confeſſed his ſinnes, and was mightily afraide of them, but yet deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired not, but confeſſed, &amp; deſired thy grace and mercy which thou gaueſt to him willingly and plentifully. Alſo Saint <hi>Peter</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied thee: and <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> in her ſinfull liuing: And haſt alſo reſpected <hi>Mathew</hi> the Cuſtomer in open eſtate, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a raging and earneſt perſecutour of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: Alſo in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Dauid,</hi> King <hi>Manaſſes</hi> the Tyrant, and other ſinners
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15111:28"/>more, which thou didſt bring to repentance and confeſſion of their ſins; and of pure loue, grace and mercy (which thou didſt reueal vnto them by thy holy Word) haſt placed them with thee in thy Kingdome. Therfore dear God and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, will I ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my ſelf ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more, and doubt nothing thereof.</p>
                        <p>Theſe, and other godly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of worth, which thou of thy grace haſt taken out of this ſinfull life to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, are a comfort and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to mee, and all beléeuing Chriſtians, that thou waſt mercifull to them, and ſo wilt be to me, and to euery ſinner which repents, according to thy owne pure loue, which the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15111:29"/>holy Ghoſt, through faith in the Goſpell, worketh in vs both gracious and mercifull, and grants vs a happy end in ſuch acknowledging of thy Name. Which, help thou me with, and all Chriſtians (dear God) Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, which art in three inſeparable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, one only and euerlaſting GOD, for euer, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:15111:29"/>
                     <head>Heer follow certain Praiers, to call vpon God for ſtrengthening of our faith.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> LORD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ESUS CHRIST, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then mée alſo with thy holy Spirit in my feare and quaking. And admoniſh me, that I thinke vpon thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Wounds in my laſt end. And let not thy holy and bitter Paſſion bee loſt on mee poore ſinner, thou which art therefore come, that thou maiſt deſtroy the Diuels worke, and pay and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poize my ſinnes with thy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15111:30"/>hard and painfull labor: and thou which haſt ſworne, <hi>Thou wilt not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Strengthen my weak faith, and kéep mee through thy Spirit of grace and of praier, vnto a happy end, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, I confeſſe vnto thée my great and manifold ſins, and the righteous wrath of God, and euerlaſting puniſhment which I haue deſerued. But I comfort my ſelf with the great loue and pure mercy of thy Father; and pray thee (ſéeing thy bloud is more than the ſinnes of the whole
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15111:30"/>world, and thou art our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour and Aduocate) that thou wilt bee Interceſſor for mee to thy Father, that my faith doo not diminiſh, and that I neuer deſpaire of thy mercy for my ſinnes, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Praier.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my faith and truſt in thée, that I deſpair not of thy gracious mercy, nor in my greateſt ſin periſh in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleef. O Lord, preſerue for mee thy promiſed grace in the holy Goſpell: let it not come out of my heart. Thou art my onely comfort and hope: ſtand to me in this my
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15111:31"/>ſorrow. Let not my poor ſoule come into the hands of my horrible. Aduerſary, and giue him no power ouer me. But ſhew mee thy goodnes at this preſent: for thou art my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and Redéemer, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, I pray thee, through thy goodnes and mercy, that thou wilt ſtrengthen my ſoule vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy holy way which lyeth before me, into thy heauenly and euerlaſting Kingdome.</p>
                        <p>I beléeue, that thou diedſt for my ſake, haſt of thy grace and mercy forgiuen mee my ſins, and that euerlaſting life is promiſed to mee. Of this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15111:31"/>my faith, O Lord, ſhall thou be witnes, and all thy Elect: and in this faith ſhall bee my laſt Will to die therein (O Lord) in thy pure mercy. And although I through griefe, want of ſenſe, or other trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſhould fall off from the ſame yet (O Lord) let m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e not die in vnbelief and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy: but ſtrengthen and increaſe my faith, that neither ſinne, hell, nor diuell, hurt me. Thou art ſtronger, and of more power than all they: whereunto I will truſt. Lord, let me not be confounded, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:15111:32"/>
                     <head>A comfort out of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt the feare of ſinne.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>ESAY 12.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>Behold, God is my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I am ſafe, and feare not: for, God the Lord is my ſtrength, my Pſalm, and my ſaluation.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <div n="1" type="comfort">
                        <head>The firſt Comfort.</head>
                        <head type="sub">How a man ſhould comfort himſelf againſt ſin, and the juſt anger of God, out of the comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="sentence">
                           <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15111:32"/>
                           <head>The firſt comfortable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>GENESIS 3.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>The Seed of the Woman ſhall tread down the head of the Serpent.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>THis is the firſt Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Doctrine of the euerlaſting Sonne of God in Paradiſe, reuealed vnto the fallen and damned man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde; whereby he might be releaſed againe from death, Gods wrath, Sinne, Hell, and power of the Diuell, and might obtaine, through beliefe in theſe words, Comfort, Grace, Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15111:33"/>on of ſinnes, and euerlaſting life.</p>
                           <p>And with this Promiſe, haue all the holy men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted themſelues, vntill <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> two thouſand yéers long: for, héer doth GOD tell vs, that he, euen of pure loue and mercy, will ſend vnto vs (poore damned ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) his onely and deare Sount, borne of a Uirgine, to take vpon him mortall and humane fleſh and bloud; who ſhould, with his abſolute Obedience and Paſſion, pay the ranſome of our ſinnes, pacifie GOD's wrath kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by reaſon of our ſinnes, deſtroy Death through his death; and with his victory, and riſing againe, reſtore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15111:33"/>againe righteouſneſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrection, and euerlaſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>g life.</p>
                           <p>This comfort ſhould wée conceiue with faithfull harts, and bee certaine thereof, that the Diuels workes are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r ſakes, and all his power taken away; that wee neuer néed to bée afraid of ſinne, death, hell, or God's anger; but, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, true God and Man, haue gotten againe righteouſneſſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. Do did an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Chriſtian at <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>reiberge</hi> in <hi>Miſnia,</hi> in the yéere of our Lord <hi>1547,</hi> comfort himſelf with this ſentence, and got victory ouer the diuell, who did trouble him by reaſon
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15111:34"/>of his ſinnes, and GOD's wrath.</p>
                           <p>For, as hee was troubled in his ſicknes, the diuell came to him in viſible forme with Ink and Paper, and ſate him downe beſides the ſick man, and ſaid; <hi>Hee ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe his ſinnes: hee was therfore there to write them vp, and to giue ſentence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</hi> The ſicke man was affraid: but yet hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred himſelf of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, anſwered the diuel, and ſaid he ſhould write, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhould tread downe the head of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> Straight-waies the diuell vaniſhed away, and left ſuch a ſtinke behinde him in all the houſe, as if hée
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15111:34"/>would baue choaked them all.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="sentence">
                           <head>The ſecond comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>GENESIS 22.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>Through thy Seed, ſhall all the Nations of the earth bee bleſſed.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>THis is the ſecond Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Preaching of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. All other mankinde, from the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> vntill the laſt, were by nature full of wickedneſſe. God was angry with them, and became their enemy: for,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15111:35"/>there was no bleſſing with them, but curſing, becauſe they were ſinners.</p>
                           <p>But through this Man Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the onely Son of the Father, full of Grace and Truth, is the onely right Séed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> wherein all the Nations of the earth muſt bee bleſſed, if they will attaine vnto euerlaſting ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                           <p>In this Sentence, behold what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>lat. 3.</hi> where hee ſaith, <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law (for, it is written, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>urſed is that man which hangeth on a tree); that the bleſſing of Abraham might come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15111:35"/>the Gentiles in ſeſus Chriſt; And we doo receiue the promiſed Spirit through faith.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In this place Saint <hi>Paul</hi> placeth theſe two words one againſt another; Firſt, the curſe; and then, the bleſſing.</p>
                           <p>All men are of themſelues poore, curſed, and dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ed ſinners: For, as the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téenth Pſalme ſaith, <hi>They are all gone aſtray: there is none that dooth good; no, not one.</hi> Againſt the which, this bleſſed Séed bringeth the bleſſing vnto vs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemeth vs from the curſe of the Lawe, in that hée was a curſe for vs: for hee as the onely immaculate Lamb of God, hath taken our ſinnes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15111:36"/>vpon him; and, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Offred our ſinnes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his body on the Croſſe.</hi> Wee ſhould hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth bee quit from ſinne, and liue vnto righteouſnes; or, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>To come to the bleſſing by him, and to receiue the Holy Ghoſt, and be the children of God.</hi> In this beſpoken bleſſed ſéed did <hi>Abraham</hi> truſt, and was happy. <hi>Abraham beleeued alwaies on God, and it was counted to him for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="sentence">
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:15111:36"/>
                           <head>The third comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>ESAY 43.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>Thou haſt made me labor with thy ſinnes, and haſt made mee weary with thy miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds: I will wipe out thy tranſgreſſions for my names ſake, and wil not think vpon thy ſinnes.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>IN this comfortable ſaying the Lord Ieſus Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, that hee onely hath paid the ranſome and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for our ſinnes, with his bloudy ſweat, bitter paſſion &amp; death; and that hée through his owne merits hath forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15111:37"/>vs all our ſinnes, in ſuch ſort, that they ſhall be wholly put out, and cleane wiped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before the face of God, and caſt into the bottome of the ſea, as though they had neuer béen, and ſhall neuer be thought vpon.</p>
                           <p>Therefore let vs not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>es or multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of our ſinnes, that wee deſpair not of Gods mercy, as <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ain</hi> &amp; <hi>Lucas</hi> did; but c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>sfaction of our Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſus Chriſt, and ſome vpon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> words.</p>
                           <p>So did king <hi>Ezec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                    <desc>•••</desc>
                                 </gap>s</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelfe, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ay 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</hi> in his great tribulation, by reaſon of his ſinnes and the wrath of God; where hee ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15111:37"/>I was much grieued for want of comfort: but thou haſt heartily accepted of my ſoule, that it doo not periſh: for, thou caſteſt all my ſinnes behinde thee;</hi> that is, thou wilt no more know nor think vpon my ſinnes. Likewiſe did King <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo pray in <hi>Pſal. 51. Waſh me from mine iniquiry, O Lord, and clenſe me from my ſins: then ſhall I be whiter than ſnowe.</hi> For no other waſhing of anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on earth can help.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="sentence">
                           <pb n="68" facs="tcp:15111:38"/>
                           <head>The fourth comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>EZECHIEL 33.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>So ſure as I liue, ſaith the Lord, I haue no pleaſure in the death of the vngodly; but rather, that hee turne from his wickednes, and liue.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>HEER the euerlaſting Sonne of GOD, our onely Lord and Rock, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth an oath by himſelfe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hée hath no greater), as true as he is a liuing, eternal, and almighty GOD, hée will not that a ſinner die, and bée damned for euer; but that hée, in acknowledging
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15111:38"/>of his ſinnes, and ſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of Chriſts bloud and merites, in true inuocation and good pretence turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to GOD, ſo ſhall hee ſurely obtayne remiſſion of ſinnes, euerlaſting righteouſnes, and the Holy Ghoſt, with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. Vpon this deare, conſtant, and true oth, ſhould wee haue reſpect when wee are troubled by reaſon of our ſinnes, and Gods wrath, and alſo in our laſt end: and ſay or thinke, I care not now how often, and how greatly I haue ſinned, and angred my Lord God: but I look vpon the oath, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſelfe, that the true GOD hath ſworn (and hée cannot repent it) he will not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15111:39"/>the death of a ſinner: ſo will hee not alſo, that I bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but for his Sonnes ſake will forgiue mee all my ſins, and take mee with him into euerlaſting life. So did the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> comfort himſelfe and others; as, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and in the firſt chapter: <hi>It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and true</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt is comne into the world to ſaue poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="sentence">
                           <pb n="71" facs="tcp:15111:39"/>
                           <head>The fift comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>IOHN 3.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>So God loued the world, that he gaue his onely-begotten Son, that whoſoeuer beleeued on him, ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>THis is one of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Sayings in all the new Teſtament, which IESUS CHRIST (whom God the Father from heauen comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vs to hear) did himſelfe bring out of the boſome of his Father, and preached the ſame to his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15111:40"/>
                              <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>t c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                    <desc>•••</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>holar <hi>Nichodemus.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Wherein he teacheth vs his Father will, what the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall GOD is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned towards the world, that is, towards all great ſinners as euer were in the world, or yet may bee; that hée loueth them, and will not haue them loſt.</p>
                           <p>And this great loue did hée ſhewe and ſet foorth vnto vs, when-as there was no other meanes whereby the ſinnes of the world might bée taken away, Gods wrath pacified, death and hell vanquiſhed: then ſpared hee not his onely Sonne, but did let him take humane fleſh and bloud vpon him, and to fulfill all which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15111:40"/>was vnpoſſible for vs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and ſuffer all payne and puniſhment, which all the world with their ſinnes had deſerued.</p>
                           <p>Whereby Gods righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe might bee fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and wee releaſed from the curſe of the Lawe.</p>
                           <p>This purchaſed treaſure, through the onelie perfect ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, the Holie-Ghoſt doth put into the Word of the Goſpel, &amp; into the holie Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and cauſeth to bée preferred to the whole world.</p>
                           <p>All that beleeue, that is, which doe acknowledge this onely Sauiour, and comfort themſelues with heartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuge to his demerits, ſhall not be loſt, but haue eternall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15111:41"/>life. Therefore, let vs out of theſe words, learne to know Gods gracious will and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue, and comfort our ſelues againſt all tribulations, againſt ſinne, and againſt the Lords an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>er.</p>
                           <p>Theſe ſayings the deare and godly man Maſter Doctor <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Prince <hi>Iohn Fredericke,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> of godly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, haue had in their laſt houre, for a happie comfort; and ſo departed both of them happily, and with merry and quiet conſciences.</p>
                           <p>And euen ſo did the poore Publican comfort himſelfe in the Temple, <hi>Luke</hi> the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téenth chapter, when he did pray vnto the Lord, <hi>God be
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15111:41"/>mercifull vnto mee a poore ſinner:</hi> that is to ſay, a wicked creature am I, and the moſt part of the world: but I doe recomfort my ſelfe with the fountaine of pure mercy, and endleſſe loue of my moſt déere God, which he hath manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vnto me in the paſſion and oblation of his onelie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne our Redéemer Ieſus Chriſt the Righteous, who hath payed and ſatiſfied the ranſome of my ſinnes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ous tranſgreſſions, and hath pacified Gods wrath, and hath giuen vnto me euerlaſting life.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="6" type="sentence">
                           <pb n="76" facs="tcp:15111:42"/>
                           <head>The ſixt comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>MAT. 11.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>Come vnto mee, all you that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>eauie laden, and I will refreſh you.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>WHat can wée heare more kindly, yea or more louingly, then that the euerlaſting Sonne of God calleth vnto him all that be weary and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in heart, and troubled for their ſinnes: and biddeth them come to his holy word, naming himſelfe a gentle and humble Teacher?</p>
                           <pb n="77" facs="tcp:15111:42"/>
                           <p>Let euery one reioyce in his heart, that God hath ſent ſuch holy comfort and refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing vpon earth; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth in plaine words, that all, whether they be poore or rich, yong or old, ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find by him, reſt, peace, ioy, refreſhing, eaſe, help, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſhall bee comforted in their ſoules, and bee made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue againe.</p>
                           <p>Therefore, when any is tormented by reaſon of his ſinnes, that he féele his heart troubled with ſorrow, and almoſt ouerthrowne with diſcomfort: Let him not creepe into a corner, or run away from the people, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> did, <hi>Geneſis 3.</hi> but let him run to the Lord Chriſt,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15111:43"/>and to theſe, and ſuch other the like comfortable words, which wee ſhall finde in the houſe of God before his face, or where God hath appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in remembrance of his name: that is, in preaching, in the holy Sacraments, and in the Writings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles: for, ſo ſoone as we ſeeke Chriſt, hée will méete vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as hée ſaith in the firſt chapter of <hi>Zacharie, Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ne ye vnto me, then will I turne vnto you</hi> So doth the Lord méete <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> a poore troubled ſinner, from whom our Lord and Sauior had before caſt out ſeuen di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, and maketh himſelfe knowne vnto her ſoone after his reſurrection, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15111:43"/>her heartily, when ſhee ſought him, <hi>Iohn 20.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="7" type="sentence">
                           <head>The ſeuenth comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>ROM. 5.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>But where Sinne is mighty, there is Grace more migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, through Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>HEere doth S <hi>Paul</hi> méet with a great tribulation, and heauy thoughts. When wee do often thinke, My ſins are too great: Oh, if I had not ſuch great ſins vpon my heart, then would I hope I ſhould be ſaued:</p>
                           <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15111:44"/>
                           <p>There doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> anſwere, <hi>If Sinne be great, yet Grace is greater,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth farre all our ſinnes: that is, one droppe of Ieſus Chriſts blood is greater, more glorious, powerfull, yea and ſtronger then all the greateſt and fearefulleſt ſinnes of the whole world: yea, as a little moat in the Sun, is not to be compared towards Heauen and Earth: ſo is the whole worlds ſinne not to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the precious blood of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                           <p>And as the cleare Sunne darkens al the ſtarres of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that they cannot be ſeene in day time (although they do ſtand in the firmament): euen ſo, when the right Sun riſing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15111:44"/>ſhineth from aboue, all ſinnes are quenched. Whoſoeuer with heartie faith catcheth hold on the bloud of Chriſt, his ſinnes are all couered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of GOD, that GOD will neuer ſée them: and is reckoned ſo cleare and holy, as if hee had troubled no water all his life time.</p>
                           <p>For the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, purgeth vs of all our ſinnes.</p>
                           <p>So did the holy Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> comfort himſelfe and his people, in the firſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where he ſaith, <hi>Though your ſins were like Purple, they ſhal be white as Wooll.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Likewiſe <hi>Dauid</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, a man after Gods owne
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15111:45"/>heart, in his déepeſt hell &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation comforteth himſelfe thus, <hi>with the Lord is mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ie and much redemption,</hi> as in the hundred and <hi>30.</hi> Pſalme: for the more ſins that Chriſt forgiueth vs, the more is his praiſe, honor, and glory: as he himſelfe teacheth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth chapter of Saint <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel, where he doth ſpeake of the great and open ſinner; <hi>To her are many ſinnes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, becauſe ſhee loued much. But to whom little is forgiuen, the ſame loueth little.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="8" type="sentence">
                           <pb n="83" facs="tcp:15111:45"/>
                           <head>The eightth comfortable Sentence.</head>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q>
                                 <bibl>
                                    <hi>PSAL 16.</hi>
                                 </bibl>
                                 <p>I thanke the Lord that hath counſelled me.</p>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                           <p>WHenas the firſt man (through the craft of the old poiſoned and fierie Serpent, and through their diſobedience) fell into ſinne, Gods wroth, and iuſtice, which after ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded vpon all <hi>Adams</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; there was no comfort, not counſell to ſinde, except the helpe and redemption of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                           <pb n="84" facs="tcp:15111:46"/>
                           <p>But through the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full counſell of the high and godly Maieſtie, at the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the onely and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Mediatour, our Lord Chriſt, it was concluded, that the Sonne of almighty God, borne of the Father euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, ſhould take humane Nature vpon him, pacifie Gods fierce and iuſt anger, and bring vs out of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels power, and euer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and help vs, from whence he carrieth the name: ſo that <hi>Flay</hi> the Prophet, in the ninth chapter (amongſt other glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious names) calleth him a <hi>Counſeller.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now when wée are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed by reaſon of our manifold ſinnes and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15111:46"/>then let vs cauſe ſuch help, as a harty and true counſell, to be brought before vs, by preaching of the holie Goſpel.</p>
                           <p>And let it be preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that through confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his gracious help and redemption, wée ſhall be quit of our ſinnes, releaſed from death, and obtaine his grace, righteouſneſſe, and euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life.</p>
                           <p>This is ſuch a true coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, that in all tribulations we may ſtade, and haue ſome comfort therein: which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did acknowledge, and thereforre ſaith, <hi>Had it not beene for thy Word, I had periſhed in my miſerie, Pſal. 119.</hi> and heere hee giueth the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15111:47"/>Lord harty thanks for all ſuch mereifull comfort and help: <hi>I thank the Lord my GOD, which hath counſelled mee</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>For, this is alſo a counſell of ſuch power, that if a man ſhould now depart out of this life, and that neither goods, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iends, riches, mony, or gold, nor any other temporall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or thing, wherein he had peraduenture héere to fore put his truſt, can counſell or help; yet hath he heere by Chriſts word, a ſure and certayne comfort, and a powerfull counſell, whereby hee ſhall bee r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ght and well, yea proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and bee holpen for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                           <p>This dee the poore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians acknowledge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15111:47"/>Therefore, when they ſhould depart out of this miſcrable life, and leaue all that is tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, they doe take hold of this happie comfort and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the holy Goſpel in their hearts, and die therein happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thus Saint <hi>Peter</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe, <hi>Iohn 6. Thou haſt the word of life.</hi> And the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the firſt chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, The Goſpel of Chriſt Ieſus, is the power of of God to ſaluation to all that beleeue.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="88" facs="tcp:15111:48"/>
                           <head>How a man ſhould comfort him ſelfe againſt ſinne, and Gods iuſt indignation. Other ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral comfortable ſentences.</head>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>ESAY 1.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>IF your ſinnes were redde like blood, yet ſhall they bee white as Snow: and if they were like purple, they ſhall be like wooll.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 2.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>The Lord will not iudge according to the ſight of his eies, nor puniſh according to the hearing of his eares: But will with righteouſnes iudge the poore.</p>
                           </q>
                           <pb n="89" facs="tcp:15111:48"/>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 6.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Thou kéepeſt continuall peace, according to ſure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for man relyeth vpon thée: Therefore rely you vpon the Lord alwaies, for God the Lord is an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Rocke.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 27.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>God is not angry with me.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 38.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Thou haſt heartily accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Soule that it periſh not, for thou haſt caſt all my ſins backward behind thee.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 40.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Comfort my people (ſaith your God) ſpeake faire to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15111:49"/>leru <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>r, and preach to her, that her warrefare is at air end, her miſde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>des are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, for ſhee hath receiued double from the hands of the Lord for all her ſinnes.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 44.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Iſrael,</hi> dee not forget mee, I driue away thy miſdeeds like a cloud, and thy ſinnes like a miſt. Turne thee vnto me, for I haue red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>emed thee. Reioyce, yee Heauens, for the Lord hath done it.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 53.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Hée was wounded for our miſdeeds, and beaten for our ſins: The puniſhment was laid vpon him, that we might haue peace, and through his
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15111:49"/>wounds are wee healed.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 53.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Through his knowledge ſhall my righteous Seruant make many righteous, for he beareth their ſinne.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 64.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Thou Lord art our Father and Redeemer; from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning hitherto, that was thy name.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Eſay 66.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I haue reſpect to the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and him that is of a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, which is afraid of my Word.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>
                                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>zechiel 33.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>So ſure as I liue, I will
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15111:50"/>not ſhe death of a ſinner, but that hée turne from his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and liue.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Dan. 9.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>In the Lord our God is mercifulneſſe, and forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Zachary 9.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Thou redeemeſt alſo through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of thy Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, thy Priſoners out of the pit wherein is no water.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Micheas 7.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Who is ſuch a God as thou art, which forgiueſt ſins, and releaſeſt miſdeeds?</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Ierem.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Hée is mercifull, hee will
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15111:50"/>take pitty on vs againe, put downe our wickedneſſe, and caſt all our ſins into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Sea.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Ionas 4.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I know that thou art gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, mercifull, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and of great goodneſſe, and repenteſt thée of euill.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Pſal. 13.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I hope vpon thée, becauſe thou art ſo merciful, my heart reioyceth that thou ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly helpeſt.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Pſal. 25.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>The Lord is good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, therefore directeth hée ſinners vpon the right way.</p>
                           </q>
                           <pb n="94" facs="tcp:15111:51"/>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Pſal. 22.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I ſaid, I will confeſſe my tranſ reſſions vnto the Lord: and thou forgaueſt mee the inquity of my ſinne.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Pſal. 31.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I rejoyced and was glad in thy goodneſſe, that thou didſt conſider my miſery, and know my ſoule in his need.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Iohn 3.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>God hath ſent his Sonne into the world, not to iudge the world, but that the world through him might bee ſaued. Whoſoeuer beléeueth on him ſhall not bee iudged.</p>
                           </q>
                           <pb n="95" facs="tcp:15111:51"/>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Iohn 3</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Like as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſifted vp the Serpent in the Wilderneſſe, ſo muſt the Sonne of man bee lifted vp, to the end that all which beleeue in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Iohn 1.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>This is the Lambe of God which taketh away the ſins of the world.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Iohn 6.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>This is the will of him which ſent mee, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer looketh on the Son, and beléeueth in him, hath euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day.</p>
                           </q>
                           <pb n="96" facs="tcp:15111:52"/>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Iohn 6.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Verily, verily, I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, whoſoeuer beleeueth on mee, hath euerlaſting life.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Math. <hi>1. The Angell ſaith of Chriſt.</hi>
                                 </hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Hée ſhall ſaue his people from their ſinnes.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Mathew 9.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I am come to call ſinners to repentance, and not the righteous.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Luke 24.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Thus it is written; and ſo muſt Chriſt ſuffer. And in his name doe they preach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and forgiueneſſe of ſins amongſt all people.</p>
                           </q>
                           <pb n="97" facs="tcp:15111:52"/>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Acts 4.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>There is no other ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor any other name giuen to mankinde, whereby they ſhould be ſaued.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Acts 10.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Of Chriſt doo all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets witneſſe, that through his Name, all they which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in him, ſhould receiue remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1. Tim. 1.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>This is a true and worthy Saying, that Ieſus Chriſt is comne into the world to ſaue poor ſinners.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1. Tim. 2.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>There is one GOD, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15111:53"/>one Mediatour betwirt God and man; namely, the Man Chriſt Ieſus, who gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for vs, to the redemption of all.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Iohn 2.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>If any man ſinne, we haue an Aduocate with GOD the Father, Ieſus Chriſt, who maketh vs righteous, and hee is the atonement for our ſinnes.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Iohn 4.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>GOD hath loued vs, and ſent his Son for a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſins.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Peter 2.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Chriſt hath offered vp our ſinnes himſelfe with his body
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15111:53"/>vpon the Croſſe; to the end we might be frée from ſinne, and liue vnto righteouſneſſe: through whoſe wounds you are healed.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Cor. 1.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Chriſt is made to vs from God, for righteouſnes, glory, and redemption.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Theſ. 5.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>GOD hath not appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs to wrath, but to attaine ſaluation through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which died for vs.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Pet. 1.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Ye are not redéemed with tranſitorie ſiluer or gold, but with the moſt precious bloud
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15111:54"/>of Chriſt like a guiltleſſe and vnſpotted Lamb.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1. Iohn 1.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt maketh vs cleane from all ſinne.</p>
                           </q>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Mat. 9.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Be comforted, my ſonne: thy ſins are forgiuen thée.</p>
                           </q>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="comfort">
                        <head>The ſecond comfort againſt ſin, and the right wrath of God, out of examples of holy Scripture.</head>
                        <p>BEſides theſe mercifull promiſes, God hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many comfortable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15111:54"/>to bee written in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures; how hee hath taken the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to mercy, when they haue méekely acknowledged and confeſſed their ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued in Ieſus Chriſt, and amended their liues; and all for the comfort of vs poore ſinners.</p>
                        <p>For, when ſinne and Gods wrath is rightly felt in our harts, ſome man is ſomtimes ſo troubled therewith, that no comfortable Sayings will enter into the heart: but hée thinks alwaies; Ah! GOD ſpeaks not of ſuch great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as thou art.</p>
                        <p>But, that the mercifull God not onely promiſeth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of all great and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15111:55"/>ſinnes, but ſheweth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo indéed, what ſinners and wicked people hee hath iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; he hath ſet downe diuers examples, which in our feare and deſpaire wee may ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs for a ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
                        <p>Firſt, as theſe: firſt, <hi>Adam</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e, the greateſt ſinners, blaſphemers, and murderers of all mankinde; by whoſe ſins and diſobedience, all ſin, ſhame, death, and euerlaſting damnation, came ouer all men: and yet GOD made them pure and holy, after his owne Image.</p>
                        <p>Then when they were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into ſin and diſobedience, GOD ſhewed this mercy vnto them, and receiued them
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15111:55"/>again, for the promiſed bleſſed Séeds ſake, as the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall Promiſe was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to them for a comfort, <hi>Geneſis 3.</hi> which they beſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, though they had no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the forgiueneſſe of ſins.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, <hi>Abraham</hi> was an idolatrous man, and ſerued the idols of <hi>Vr</hi> in <hi>Chaldea:</hi> to him did GOD giue the Promiſe of the bleſſed Séed, and made him a Father of all Beléeuers, that is, as <hi>Eſay</hi> in his fortith Chapter repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; <hi>Comfort my people,</hi> ſaith the Lord: <hi>for, their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes are forgiuen, and they haue receiued double from the Lords hands for all their miſdeeds.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="104" facs="tcp:15111:56"/>
                        <p>But this is double; that GOD firſt remitteth to vs the ſinne, and releaſeth to vs the puniſhment of the ſinne, and after giueth vs withall euerlaſting righteouſnes and ſaluation, that wee may liue and raigne with him in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting righteouſnes, ioy and glory.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, <hi>Dauid,</hi> though an abominable wedlock-breaker and murderer, hath forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſins for Chriſt's ſake, and is ſaued for euer.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> the cruell and raging tyrant, who with a Saw cauſed the holy Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> to bee cut in ſunder (when he had preached eighty yeers in great pain and labour) and ſpilled much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15111:56"/>blood, ſet vp all heathniſh idolatry, letting his owne ſon paſſe through the fire; and laſtly, offred him vp aliue to <hi>Moloch:</hi> then, when he was in priſon, he turned and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe vnto God, and prayed him with teares; the Lord God did heare him, and brought him again to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, to the earthly and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Kingdom, <hi>2 Kings 27.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Fiftly, what a great ſinner was the thief on Chriſts right hand, and other intolerable Vſurers &amp; Publican ſinners!</p>
                        <p>Sirtly, how groſſely haue the deare Apoſtles oft-times gon aſtray! How horribly fel Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> when he denied his Maſter, in taking-vpon him ſo much, &amp; curſed himſelf!</p>
                        <pb n="106" facs="tcp:15111:57"/>
                        <p>What innocent bloud did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> help to ſpil, when he was a perſecuter of Chriſt his Congregation! For all theſe Chriſt prayed, forgaue them all their ſinnes, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them for euer. Alſo through them hee did much good in Chriſtendome.</p>
                        <p>Seuenthly, Chriſt alſo had many ſinners in his kinred, and are ſo regiſtred, which were his Grandfathers and Grandmothers according to the fleſh; as, <hi>Iuda</hi> the bloud-thirſty, <hi>Rachab</hi> the common Harlot and Heathen at <hi>Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho;</hi> to ſhew thereby, that he was comne into this world to ſaue ſinners.</p>
                        <p>Theſe examples hath Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD (through
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15111:57"/>the holy Ghoſt) written vp for the learning and comfort of vs poor and wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that wée ſhould beleeue, God will forgiue vs all our ſinnes for his Sonnes ſake, as often and as horribly as wée haue offended, not that wée ſhould thinke our ſelues ſafe, and preſumptuouſly ſin on ſuch mercy of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ord, but that we might haue a ſure comfort and conſolation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne and damnation, that wée deſpaire not by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our ſinnes, or flée away from Chriſt: which is the onely ſin whereby the world was damned, <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téenth Chapter: As the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſheweth vs this profit, <hi>1 Tim. 1.</hi> where
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15111:58"/>hee writeth thus: <hi>This is a true Saying, that Ieſus Chriſt is comne into the world to ſaue ſinners; among which, I am the chief.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But mercy is ſhewed to me in this reſpect, that Ieſus Chriſt hath ſhewed patience on mee for example, that all that beléeue in him, ſhould haue euerlaſting life. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to God the eternal king, the vntranſitory, inuiſible, and onely wiſe God, bee all praiſe and glory for euer, Amen.</p>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <pb n="109" facs="tcp:15111:58"/>
                           <head>A Praier.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou onely Fountaine of all grace and mercy, thou neuer didſt deny thine endleſs mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, neither to <hi>Mathew,</hi> nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Publican, nor <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> nor the loſt ſonne, nor to <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Zacheus</hi> the Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, nor to the Thief on the Croſſe, nor yet to any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. Thou haſt ſpoken with fatherly &amp; comfortable ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Come vnto me, all you that labour and are heauy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> O take care of mee, and look vpon mee with thine eyes of godly compaſſion, euen as thou didſt look vpon <hi>Peter,</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="110" facs="tcp:15111:59"/>
                           <p>I, a poor and vnworthy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, doo ſtand before thée, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with ſo many great ſins and offenſes, that, by reaſon thereof, I cannot look vp, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both abaſhed and aſham'd before that godly Maieſtie whom I haue grieuouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and knowe not what to ſay. O Lord, be mercifull to me a wretched ſinner: turn away thy wrath, and impart thy mercy with me. Which I do deſire with hearty tears, through the merits of Chriſt Ieſus our alone Lord and Redéemer.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="comfort">
                        <pb n="111" facs="tcp:15111:59"/>
                        <head>The third comfort againſt ſinne and Gods wrath, out of the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</head>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 4.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>THe Lord ſhal waſh away the filthineſſe from the daughter of Sion, and ſhall purge the bloudy ſinne from Ieruſalem by the Spirit of iudgement, and by the Spirit of burning.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 12.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>With ioy and conſolation ſhall you draw water from out of the Well of Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                        </q>
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:15111:60"/>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Zach. 13.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>At that time ſhall the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the Citizens of Ieruſalem, haue a free and open Well againſt ſinne and vncleanneſſe.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Mark 16.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>Whoſoeuer beléeueth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaued.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Acts 2.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, Repent, and let euery one bée baptized in the Name of Ieſus Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iſt our Sauiour for the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Iohn 20.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>Chriſt ſaith to his Apoſtles, Receiue the holy Ghoſt:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15111:60"/>whoſe ſins you forgiue, they are forgiuen.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Mat. 26.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>Chriſt ſaith, This is my bloud of the new teſtament, which is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins.</p>
                        </q>
                        <p>BEcauſe oftentimes tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation &amp; grief is ſo great, and ſorrow with the combate of death ſo ouertakes vs, that we cannot haſtily, and in ſuch great weakneſſe, remember our ſelues of any ſentence or example; and that a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins often to deſpair whether God hath forgiuen him his ſinnes, and will be mercifull to him, and if Chriſts bloud eſpecially bee ſhed for him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15111:61"/>ſo: there hath the Lord, of his great loue, not onely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs his holy promiſe, and ſet downe comfortable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, eſpecially the holy and worthy Sacraments; that is to ſay, Baptiſm, and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Supper: which hee hath inſtituted and ordained for remiſſion of ſinnes, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all them that are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in his bloud, and abſolueth euery one of all their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, that hée may bée ſure hée is alſo cleare thereof in heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n before the face of God; and féedeth euery one ſeuerally with his Body and precious Bloud, to the end hée may bee aſſured, Chriſts Bloud was ſhed for his ſins, and his Body offred vp alſo
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15111:61"/>for his miſ-déeds, and giueth the ſame to euery one that receiueth the ſame (in true Faith, acknowledging his ſinnes, and in good pretenſe) all and what ſoeuer hee hath earned and obtained with his Obedience, Death, and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                        <p>With this holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould wee admoniſh and comfort our ſelues, when ſorrow, and the combate of death, is at the greateſt, that wee cannot remem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er any thing elſe; and think and ſay thus much in our hearts: I am baptized; whereby God the holy Trinity, hath made an euerlaſting couenant with mée, that he will bée and continue my GOD, and hath
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15111:62"/>not grounded the ſame vpon my goodnes, but vpon his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy, the merits of his onely Sonne, and vpon the grace and power of the holy Ghoſt. So am I abſolued through Chriſt, and haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes receiued the holy ſupper of the Lord according to his inſtitution: therefore I am certaine of the forgiuenes of all my ſins, Gods grace, and ſaluation of my ſoule.</p>
                        <p>For, if the euerlaſting, mercifull God, and my Lord Ieſus, with the holy Ghoſt, would not haue mee ſaued, or taken me to mercie, he would not haue ſuffered mee to be baptized, or called mee to his Kingdome through his holy Goſpell, nor let mee ſo often
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15111:62"/>receiue the holy Sacrament.</p>
                        <p>Therefore ſhould we haue theſe worthy Sacraments in great eſtimation, and often reſort to the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord, vſing the ſame in right worthineſſe for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming of our faith, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort againſt ſin, and the wrath of God in our laſt end.</p>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <pb n="118" facs="tcp:15111:63"/>
                           <head>A Prayer.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>O</hi> Thou euerlaſting, true, mercifull God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I thanke thee through Ieſus Chriſt thy deare Son, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power and vnſpeakeable ſighing of the holy Ghoſt, that thou haſt ſuffred mee to be baptized in the name and power of the holy Trinity, and taken me vp for thy child, and through power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keies haſt abſolued me from all my ſinnes, and fed mee with the body and bloud of thy deare Sonne, for the ſtrengthening of my faith, and forgiueneſſe of all my ſinnes.</p>
                           <p>And I pray thée, dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15111:63"/>that thou wilt vphould me through thy holy Spirit, in true ſaith and confidence to my end, that I may ſléep in peace like to holy <hi>Simeon,</hi> and riſe againe with the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to euerlaſting glory, through Ieſus Chriſt thy dear Sonne, our onely Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>A Praier to bee ſaid, when a man will receiue the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>O</hi> LORD <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Sonne of God, which before thy Death and Paſſion
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15111:64"/>didſt inſtitute and ordaine to all Chriſtians a new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt worthy Sacrament of thy moſt holy Body and Bloud: which I poore ſinner am not worthy to vſe, or take thy holy Body and Bloud into my vncleane mouth, or vpon my ſinnefull tongue: and that thou, béeing ſo great a Lord, ſhouldeſt come vnder the couer of my houſe, or into my vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Bodie, I am (alas!) not worthy. But I pray thée (O dear GOD and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) open thou my mouth, touch thou my tongue, and purge thou my heart from all ſinnes, and make mee thy poore ſeruant worthy of thy moſt holy Teſtament, that I
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15111:64"/>may receiue, take and vſe' thy moſt worthy bodie, and pure deare bloud of thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to the health and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of my ſoule, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my faith, amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my life, in burning loue towards thee, true loue towards my neighbour: and bring mee to euerlaſting life, Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>A Praier of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>O</hi> Almighty and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, I praiſe and thanke thy godly merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that thou haſt fed mee with the fleſh and blood of thy onely Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, my Lord and Sauiour, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15111:65"/>doe pray thee moſt humbly, thou wilt with the Holy Ghoſt ſo worke within mee, that I which haue receiued this bleſſed Sacrament with the mouth, may alſo with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant faith, conceiue and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies keepe faſt thy godly grace, of remiſſion of ſinnes, and iuſtification with Chriſt, which is therein ſhewed and promiſed, and euerlaſting life through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt thy deare Sonne, who with thee in vnitie of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt liueth and rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, one true God for euer and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:15111:65"/>
                     <head>A godly confeſſion of the deare and worthy man <hi>M. Iohn Stoliz.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MY ſins doe trouble mee.</p>
                     <p>Gods grace ioyeth me.</p>
                     <p>Two things know I,</p>
                     <p>A poore ſumer am I,</p>
                     <p>God is mereifull:</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>The firſt, acknowledge I;</item>
                        <item>The ſecond, beléeue I.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>O God bée mereifull to mée poore ſinner.</p>
                     <p>God giueth.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt meriteth.</p>
                     <p>Faith conceiueth.</p>
                     <p>Workes do witneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Come to helpe mee, thou good God; weake is mans helpe in tune of need.</p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:15111:66"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 42.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>The bruiſed Reede ſhall bee not breake, and the glowing Tow ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ee n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t quench out. O Lord strengthen &amp; increaſe our faith, Amen.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Gods gracious and euer laſting Prouidence and Maintenance, a moſt true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalme 37.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>WHen I haue but thee (my Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt) I care not for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or earth. When my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule fayle mee, yet art thou alwaies God, the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15111:66"/>comforter of my heart, and portion.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Zachary 12.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>OVer the houſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> and ouer the Citizens of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> will I powre out the Spirit of Grace, and of Prayer, for they ſhall looke vpon mée, whom they haue pearced.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>HEere doth the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſend his Holy Ghoſt to vs poore ſinners, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>15.</hi> and <hi>16.</hi> Chapters, often maketh mention of this promiſe: for becauſe wée are weake and of little faith, when ſinne and Gods wrath doe terrifie vs, to the end our faith ceaſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15111:67"/>not, then ſhall the Holy-ghoſt (as a true Comforter) ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and comfort vs, and bee witneſſe to our hearts, that our ſinnes bee forgiuen, and that weere in grace, and ſhe children of GOD, and ſhall help vs to ſigh and pray with vnſpeakeable ſighing.</p>
                     <p>Therewithall alſo ſhall the How-ghoſt for the comfort &amp; ſtrengthening of our faith, admoniſh and ſhew vs the holy wounds, whereby wee may acknowledge, that he was wounded and pearced for our ſins, and his blood ſhed for the clenſing and waſhing away of all our ſinnes.</p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:15111:67"/>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>II. Eſay 54.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>SO haue I ſworne, that I will not bée angrie with thee, nor yet reprooue thee: for the Mountaines ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moone, and the hills ſhall fall away; but my Grace ſhall not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oe away from thee, and the Conenant of my Peace ſhall not fall away, ſaith the Lord thy compaſſioner.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>GOd the Almighty hath (through Chriſt, his heſt beloued Sonne) erected a Conenant of peace with vs, and confirmed the ſame with an doth, That if we do beleeue in Chriſt, hee will not puniſh, nor yet concernne vs for euermore, but continue
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15111:68"/>our deare and louing Father eternally.</p>
                     <p>Such promiſe is ſo certaine, that the Mountaines ſhall fall down; yea Heauen and Earth ſhall paſſe away, before ſuch words faile.</p>
                     <p>A very glorious and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable cauſe doth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſet héereunto. <hi>The Lord thy Compaſſioner hath ſaid;</hi> that is, God is ſo mercifull, that hee will not condemne you for your ſinnes: Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beléeueth in Chriſt with a faithfull heart, ſhall reſt in grace, and hee will for euer releaſe and helpe him out of all misfortune.</p>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:15111:68"/>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>III. Eſay 54.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Feare them not, thou ſhalt not bée aſhamed. Bee not weake, for thou ſhalt not bée mocked.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>THESE are faire and comfortable words. The Holy Ghoſt ſeeth how fleſh and bloud doe forment vs Chriſtians; for although they haue exceeding promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſure comfort, yet is this weakeneſſe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by it, that their hearts bee fearefull, and weake. They are aſtoniſhed at the diuels power, and are afraide by reaſon of their vnable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for becauſe examples doe ſtand before our eyes,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15111:69"/>how God doth ſometime let the godly fall, therefore feare they the like will happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: but God comforteth them, they ſhall not bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nor mocked: that is, God will not let them die or periſh in their ſinnes, but he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déene them and help them for euer. For, to bee aſhamed is nothing elſe in the Scripture, but when hope faileth and is in vaine.</p>
                     <p>So the Rich man hoped in his money &amp; goods, but he was aſhamed therby; for a thouſand things may happen to them, where neyther money nor goods will help at all. So muſt therbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhamed, who hope vpon I clatrie, &amp; their owne goodneſſe. But they which
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15111:69"/>ſet their hope on God, that hee will, for Chriſts ſake, bée mercifull, and help, and ſaue them, this hope is ſure, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them not be aſhamed. So did <hi>Dauid</hi> comfort himſelfe, <hi>Pſalme 31. Vpon thee doe I truſt, let me not be aſhamed, releaſe me through thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>III. Eſay 54.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Thou ſhalt bée prepared through righteouſnes Thou ſhalt bee farre from force and wrong, that thou needeſt not bée afraide thereof, for it ſhall not come neere thee.</p>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:15111:70"/>
                     <p>HEere muſt thou not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe wordes, force, wrong and feare, temporally; for with Chriſtians héere it ſhall not bée otherwiſe, but that they ſhall bée oppreſſed, and ſundry wayes made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, as Experience ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>In the world you ſhall haue ſorrow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the Holy Ghoſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of Force, Wrong, and Feare, that is euer and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally; from which Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are ſledde away through remiſſion of ſinnes (which they beléeue through Chriſt) for they know that GOD is their Father: although he let them ſuffer corporally, they comfort themſelues with his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15111:70"/>helpe and grace, and know, whileſt they haue Chriſt, they cannot miſſe.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>V. Eſay 49.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sion</hi> ſaith, The Lord hath forſaken me: The Lord hath forgotten me. Can a woman forget her Childe, that ſhée take not pitty of the ſonne of her body? and although ſhée ſhould forget it, yet will I not forget thee: Behould, I haue marked thee in the very hand.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>When the Lord God a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſuffereth vs to fall into ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent need, croſſe, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and helpeth not quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; then faileth often-times our comfort, and we thinke God hath forgotten vs. In
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15111:71"/>ſuch tribulation, hee ſheweth vs a comfortable Image to looke vpon, and to learne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſtrengthen our faith.</p>
                     <p>Thou art (ſaith he) a father or mother, &amp; haſt louing chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: tell me, if thy child ſhould be for a while from thee, coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou forget it? Oh no, it is impoſſible for any that are in their right wits, or that haue any reaſon or vnderſtanding: for children come from the heart, and goe to the heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
                     <p>But to me, ſaith the Lord, it is more impoſſible, for my heart is not ſo ſickle as mans, neither is my grace ſo ſhort or narrow.</p>
                     <p>I haue an eternall grace and mercy; therefore can I
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15111:71"/>as little forget my Chriſtians as mine hand, they are noted in my hand.</p>
                     <p>I thinke on them continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, they are alwayes before my godly eies, that I muſt ſee them, and cannot forget them, yea &amp; doe vphold them alſo, through the right hand of my Righteouſnes, ſo that no man, neither Sinne, Hell, Death, nor Diuell, can by any meanes pull them out of my hand.</p>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:15111:72"/>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>VI. Pſal. 8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thou haſt put all things vnder his feete.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <p>WEe poore Creatures are afraid of this vile naughty world, the Turke, Death, and his beggerly ſickneſſe, and of the very Diuell, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide of his tyranny and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh power, which is naturall: but when wee acknowledge our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and what power and might hée hath, wherefore neede we be afraid? As the Church ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very comfortably out of the ſixe and fortie Pſalme.</p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:15111:72"/>
                     <q>
                        <l>If all the world fell diuels were, and would vs all deuoure:</l>
                        <l>Yet need we not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to ſeare, of vs they haue no power.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>For this Champion, which is alwaies our Sauiour and <hi>Emanuel,</hi> is alwayes by vs, and hath ſuch power to defend vs, and to vphold vs, that hee will bee our ſtedfaſt rocke and bulwarke againſt all our Aduerſaries, Sinne, Death, and the Diuell, and preſerue vs euermore: for God the Father hath put all things vnder his feete.</p>
                     <p>And this ſaying muſt not bee vnderſtood of Sheepe, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, wilde beaſts, and Fiſhes of the Sea, but by this word <hi>(All)</hi> vnderſtand all Diuels, all helliſh rabblement, Turks,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15111:73"/>and Heathens: <hi>In ſumm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> the very gates of Hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Plague, Peſtilence, &amp;c. is all put vnder Chriſts ſeet, that is to ſay, vnder his power.</p>
                     <p>Therefore is it a ſure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto vs, that wee haue a ſtrong couragious Lord to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs. For all the Diuels (how horrible ſoeuer they ſeeme) with all their armies and helliſh power, are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make a Chriſtian die, without the will of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, they muſt all acknowledge him to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>rd, and now the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. When dare not once ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>re, rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is will; much leſſe, ſeeing hee hath with his owne blood bought
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15111:73"/>vs to his euerlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and will not hinder vs of our ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>This comfort ſhould eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Chriſtian bée ſure of, that hée may ſay, I beléeue in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>I am certaine that Ieſus Chriſt is Lord of heauen and Earth; yea, of all in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the depth of Hell: that hee hath all in his hands, in his power and command, in ſuch ſort, that all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, Hell, and Death, how raging ſoeuer they bee, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not crooke a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ire of mée, or of any member of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, all diſeaſes, ſickneſſe, or peſtilence, without his will, cannot poyſon one little veine in mee: But if it doe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15111:74"/>with his will, then muſt it not bee hurtfull vnto mee, but a furtherance and ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to my ſaluation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A praier.</head>
                     <p>O My God, my Lord, and Father, ſhew vnto my poore ſoule, that it may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thou art my rocke, bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark, ſhield, tower, treaſure, defence, truſt, helpe, refuge, protection and goodneſſe; that I in this my great néede and tribulation, may, through thy godly grace, haue help and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt my aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and bee preſerued for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                     <p>Lord, vpon thee do I truſt,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15111:74"/>let me neuer be aſhamed.</p>
                     <p>Into thy hands, O Lord, I commend my Spirit: O Lord, thou true God, releaſe thou me, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Generall comfortable Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherewith a man may comfort himſelfe with Gods eternall preſeruation.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Eſay 41.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>THOU ſhalt bée my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, for I haue choſen thee, and caſt thee not away. Feare not, I am with thée. Goe not aſide, for I am thy
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15111:75"/>God, I ſtrengthen thee, I helpe thee alſo, and I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thee through the right hand of my Righteouſnes.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Eſay 43.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Feare thou not, I haue redeemed thee, I haue called thee by thy Name, thou art mine.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalme 31.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Lord, on thee doe I truſt, let mee neuer bée confounded, deliuer mee through thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be comforted, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, all you that tarry for the Lord.</p>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:15111:75"/>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 32.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The vngodly hath many ſorrowes, but hee that truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Lord, ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with goodneſſe.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 91.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Though a thouſand fall at thy ſide, and tenne thouſand on thy right hand, yet ſhall it not touch thee.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 91.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Vpon the Lion and Adder ſhalt thou goe, and tread vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the young Lion and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 23.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Goodneſſe and merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall follow mee all my
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15111:76"/>life time: and I ſhall dwell in the houſe of the Lord for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iohn 14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>In my Fathers houſe are many dwellings: if it were not ſo, I would haue told you: I goe hence to prepare the places for you.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iohn 14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I will not leaue you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe: I liue, and you ſhall alſo liue.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iohn 14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I will come againe, and take you vnto mee, that you may be where I am.</p>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:15111:76"/>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iohn 12.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Where I am, there ſhall alſo my ſeruant be.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When I ſhall be lifted vp from the earth, then will I draw them all vnto me.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iohn 10.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I knowe my ſhéep, and am knowne of mine: and no man ſhall pull them out of mine hands.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom. 8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>If God bée with vs, who ſhall bée againſt vs? who alſo hath not ſpared his onely ſon, but hath giuen him for vs; how can hes not but giue vs
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15111:77"/>all with him?</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom. 8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I am ſure, that neither death nor life, neither Angell nor principality, nor power, neither things preſent, nor to come, neither height, nor depth, nor any other creature, can ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord, Amen.</p>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer.</head>
                     <p>LAud, praiſe and thankes, bee vnto thée, my Lord Ieſus Chriſt, for thy holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, for thy martyrdom and litter paſſion; out of which I acknowledge, that
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15111:77"/>thou art my Redéemer and Sauiour; and do beléeue, that thou haſt ouercome ſin, death, hell, and the diuell, that they cannot hurt me. With this onely doo I comfort me: héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon build I: there ſtandeth my hope: there will I bée found. Onely bee gracious and mercifull vnto mee, as I doubt not of thy ſure promiſe. O Lord, let mee not ſink or deſpaire in this my great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and neceſſity, but preſerue mee happily by ſuch ſure comfort, Amen.</p>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:15111:78"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 49.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>Thou ſhalt vnderſtand that I am the Lord; of whom they ſhall not bee aſhamed, which tarry for me, &amp;c.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A comfort for poore ſicke people, which are troubled by reaſon of their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſicknes.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Pſal. 118.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>THe Lord thaſtiſeth mée, but giueth me not ouer to death.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Pſal. 119.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>It is good for mée that thou
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15111:78"/>haſt chaſtiſed me, that I may learn thy Lawes.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>WHen any outward miſ-fortune, croſſe or ſickneſſe falleth vpon vs, then are wée ſundry waies aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: wée behaue our ſelues impatiently, and doo comolain and wéep for it. Such im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience is a great torment to a Chriſtian: for, when the diuell can doo nothing elſe on him, then commeth he with impatience, that many in their miſeries doo ſnarle and powt.</p>
                     <p>But if we could remember this onely word, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is good, Lord, that thou haſt chaſtiſed mee;</hi> we ſhould rather wéepe and cry
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:15111:79"/>when we are without croſſes, ſickeneſſe, or other aduerſity. But, what proſit or goodneſſe this Croſſe is of, ſhould euery Chriſtian earneſtly thinke on in all his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p>The chiefeſt profit of the Croſſe, is this: Firſt, that thereby fleſhly luſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may bée hindred, that it be not laſciuious, and throwe vs not into damnation, as our noereſt enemie which wée daily carry in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes: for, as a man muſt ſpurre a Horſe, and hold him with the bridle, and bring him forward, <hi>Pſalm 32.</hi> ſo muſt the Lord God alſo ſpur and bridle our olde <hi>Adam</hi> through the Croſſe; without
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:15111:79"/>which correction, wée ſhall neuer come there, whereunto woe through the Croſſe haue cauſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Then ſhall wee thereby be driuen to the Word, and to Prayer, and brought alſo to be penitent, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith; <hi>Onely miſchance and tribulation teach vs to mark the Word;</hi> or (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> chaſtiſed mee, that I might learn thy Lawes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 If it ſhould alwaies bée with vs according to our own carnall wils, then ſhould wée be proud and inſolent, &amp;c. But when God catcheth hould on vs with ſicknes or any other croſſe, then wee acknowledge our diſability.</p>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:15111:80"/>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>4</hi> Wee ſhall bee thereby occaſioned to eſteeme and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Gods gracious and almighty help; that hee is to vs a Rock, a Bulwark, Defenſe, Protection, Help and Strength in all our néed and neceſſity; without which gracious help, wée deſpaire of all things, and muſt bee without comfort. Now, when the diuell, with his poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, peſtilence, and beggerly ſickneſſe, is worſt-minded towards vs, and ſcattereth his plagues and ſickeneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, yet then haue wee Chriſtians GOD for a ſure comfort: wee are vnder his godly protection &amp; defenſe, and do truſt alwaies on Gods help; therfore ſhall we neuer
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15111:80"/>be aſhamed.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi>5</hi> Then, when wée haue obtained and gotten GOD's helpe, others ſhall in like maner be therewith ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and comforted, that they, in all their tribulation and néed, may ſet their comfort &amp; hope on the Lords gracious help.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <hi>6</hi> Although the Croſſe doo bring ſuch profit, that many more cauſes might bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed; yet the greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnder the Croſſe is, that wee bee thereby aſſured, that wee are the children of God for euer, and ſo ſhall remain; ſeeing that euery father cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth his deare childe, if hée take it vp (to the end it may bée kept in kindly obedience)
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15111:81"/>
                        <hi>Hebrews 12 Prouerbs 20.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And héer it goeth after the common Prouerb, as often as the honeſt Parents do ſay before their Children,</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>O dear Rod,</l>
                        <l>Thou makeſt me good:</l>
                        <l>Thou makeſt me ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle to be,</l>
                        <l>That the Hangman</l>
                        <l>Be not troubled with me.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Such cauſes, how fatherly ſoeuer our Lord God means, that hée layeth ſo many kinde of croſſes vpon His; and withall, the great bountifull goodneſſe and profit that the ſame tribulations bring vnto vs, let vs earneſtly thinke vpon, when we are in miſery, ſickneſſe, or other calamities,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:15111:81"/>and not murmure againſt GOD: for, he knowes his creatures beſt, and can tell what is good and profitable both for ſoule and body. So did the Lord Ieſus well ſee before, the tribulation that his Diſciples ſhould haue after his death and paſſion: but he comforted them, <hi>Iohn 16. It is good for you that I goe hence: for, if I goe not, the Comforter wil not come to you; but, if I go hence, I will ſend him to you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore ſhould wée ſet our will to GOD's will, as <hi>Syrach</hi> in the <hi>2</hi> Chap. admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth: <hi>My Childe, if thou wilt bee Gods Seruant, then prepare thee to tribulation: leane thou vnto God, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15111:82"/>ſhrink not, that thou maiſt bee alwaies ſtronger. Suffer whatſoeuer happeneth vnto thee, and bee patient in all thy troubles: for, like as gold is tried in the fire; ſo ſhall they whom God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, bee tried through the fire of aduerſity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="assault">
                     <head>I. Againſt the firſt aſſaulting vnder the Croſſe. God eſteems vs not.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 27.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>I The Lord do kéep my vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, that is, my Chriſtians, and water it quickly that his leaues doo not wither: I will
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15111:82"/>preſerue it day and night.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>Héer doth God the Lord comfort vs, that his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould not bee grieued with the Croſſe: for, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth his Chriſtendome to a pleaſant Vineyard that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth open on all ſides, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one may come in; and no man keeps it, but lets it ly, yea, that it wants rain, and all will wither and bee dry. So doo wee alſo think vnder the Croſſe, that God careth not for vs, elſe ſhould wee hée better. But it is certain, that God himſelf wil be Guardian ouer his Chriſtians, and will ſend them the rain of grace &amp; comfort in all their temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as hee héer ſaith, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>e Lord doo keep it, and will
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15111:83"/>quickly water it. I will keep it both day and night, that no man hurt it:</hi> that is, My Chriſtians ſhal not méet with any euill, ſo graciouſly will I watch and ward them. But ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> is ſuch watching and warding, and yet a man doth not ſee it?</p>
                     <p>Although it ſéemeth, God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th no great reſpect with his guar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing of temporal things, and whatſoeuer is corporall (whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt they belong not to his Kingdom), yet muſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world and the diuell let it alone, and not doo all things as pleaſeth them, ſeeing the hairs of our head are numbred: As wee haue an example thereof in <hi>Mat. 8.</hi> that the diuell, without Chriſts leaue, could not goe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:15111:83"/>into a filthy Swine. And ſuch doo the Hiſtories ſufficiently ſhew. But the right guard and protection of vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, goeth inwardly to the heart; which, God with his holy Spirit and Word puts into vs, and day and night keeps vs, that ſin growe not quite ouer vs, and that Satan be not too mighty for vs.</p>
                     <p>Of ſuch guard ſpeaketh he ſhortly after. The ſin of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſhall thereby ceaſe, that is, through the Croſſe God defends vs againſt ſinne, and mortifieth the old <hi>Adam.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Many a one doth lie in his bedde; who, if hee were well, would doo all miſchief. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a one hath another aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which driueth him to
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15111:84"/>Sermons and Praiers, and to amendment of his life; who, if that were not, would care nothing at all for God or his Word.</p>
                     <p>Againſt ſuch aſſaulting, ſhould we earneſtly think vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this defenſe of our Lord God: for, the world doth not ſée it, and the Chriſtians alſo ſomtimes do forget it in their néed, and think, God doth not regard them, he hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them. So did <hi>Dauid</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelf, <hi>Pſalm 32. Thou art my d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fenſe: thou wilt keep me from ſorrow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="161" facs="tcp:15111:84"/>
                        <head>A Praier.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou kéeper of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> which dooſt neither ſlumber nor ſléep, and haſt promiſed to thy faithfull that lift vp their eies toward hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to thee, and tarry for thy godly grace, comfort &amp; help, that thou wilt kéep them day and night in their tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and with the comfort of thy holy Spirit wilt moiſten their hearts, and graciouſly accept of them, which is eaſie for thee to doo: I pray thée, let mee not forget thy watching and warding in my aduerſity, nor bee weak in mine owne cauſe; that thou wouldſt kéep me from trouble. O kéep me
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15111:85"/>from all tribulation. O kéep me from all euill. O kéep my ſoule and deliuer me: let me not be aſhamed. O kéep thou my going out, and comming in, both now &amp; for euermore, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="assault">
                     <head>
                        <hi>II.</hi> Againſt the other a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſaulting, God is our enemy.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 27.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>With me is no anger.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Lamen. 3.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>The Lord troubleth, but he hath compaſſion again accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his great goodnes: for hee vereth not nor troubleth man from his heart.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:15111:85"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> God, whoſoeuer could beléeue this, ſhould yet bee merry although hee were ill. But all ſorrows and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints come of this, that we think, God is angry with vs. Therefore he giueth vs in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> a pleaſant ſimilitude: I cannot bee ſo angry with my Vmeyard, that is, with my Chriſtians, becauſe I attend the ſame ſo diligently. It is a deare Iewell vnto me.</p>
                     <p>Therefore doe I dreſſe it, I hack it, I cut it; not that I hate it, but becauſe I loue it, and will further it, that it bring forth fruit; which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:15111:86"/>would not come foorth, if I ſhould not in ſuch ſort hack it, and cut it: for, although it ſeem not friendly, that the hedger ſtandeth ouer the Vine with his knife, and cutteth it, hath the Mattocke in his hand, and heaweth it with all his might, yet is it but for the good of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, that it beare the more fruit.</p>
                     <p>So ſhall you, my deare Chriſtians, ſaith the Lord, vnderſtand it ſol kewiſe, and hold it for a certaine, that I loue you, <hi>Prouerbs 3.</hi> when I come ouer you with the Croſſe, with the Wine-hook and Mattocke, cut and hack you.</p>
                     <p>Another fine ſimilitude
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:15111:86"/>giueth he afterward of plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in chapter <hi>28.</hi> Hearken with your eares, and heare my voice: When a Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man breaketh and ploweth his field, it ſéemeth that hée doth much harme, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when hee oftentimes in the yéere, yea, thrée or foure times, turneth it ouer, and ploweth through the ſame. Wherefore doth hee it? It goeth heere after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prouerb; The fourth kinde bringeth the fourth Sheaf.</p>
                     <p>Therefore dooth hee not let it reſt after plowing: but when hee hath plowed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his field, hee ſoweth it; then followeth faire and goodly fruit. So, ſaith the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:15111:87"/>Lord GOD, doo I alſo. I plow you with the Croſſe, and ſend one thing after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; now pouerty, then ſickeneſſe; &amp;c. which dooth grieue you: but it procéedeth not of anger, as if I were your enemy: it is done for your good, that the ſtones and rocks may be rooted out, and the ground made readie for fruit. Therefore doe I chaſtiſe you thorow right and doctrine.</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe doth <hi>leremy</hi> in this place alſo comfort: <hi>The Lord troubleth me, &amp;c</hi> For that is his work, as Pſalm <hi>4</hi> ſaith. Hee dealeth ſtrangely with his Saints, he thruſteth them firſt unto hell, and lets them come into need, before
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15111:87"/>he do help them out: hée lets one bee firſt ſick, before hee make him whole.</p>
                     <p>But, in ſuch Croſſes and Tribulations, doth hée leaue them helpleſſe? No; but hath ſuch a heart as is full of loue and compaſſion. Therefore is hee mercifull againe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto his great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and ſheweth himſelfe like a helpfull GOD, and beareth a fatherly heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs. For, like as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooth carry an heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his deare childe, in that hee reſtraineth him, to the end he come to goodnes, and may ſee both ioy and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty in him: So in GOD's heart towards vs alſo that he vexeth not, nor troubleth vs
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15111:88"/>men from his heart, but that he may preſerue vs his deare children to his glory, kingdom and euerlaſting life.</p>
                     <p>Heer of haſt thou a fine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> which praied a long time: hee was guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and caſt into Priſon. God heard him not ſo ſoone, elſe had he come home to his parents, and béen a poor ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd all his life time: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward God took pity of his miſery, releaſed him of his impriſonment, and made him a great Prince ouer all the Land of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So will God alſo doo with vs his deare children: a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time will he leaue vs, to bée troubled in miſery: but afterwards will he accept of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:15111:88"/>vs, and take pity with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting mercy, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reioyce vs, preſerue and bring vs to euerlaſting glory.</p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord God, heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly well meaning, wilt keep me thy deare Child héere on earth vnder thy rodde, to the end I may bée like thine onely Sonne, both in paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and afterwards in glorie: I pray thee comfort mee in my tribulations and croſſes, with thy holy Spirit, that I deſpaire not; but according to the promiſes of thy Sonne, doe take ſure holde of this
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:15111:89"/>comfort, that the croſſes of me and all faithfull, be but a little, and that thou wilt with thy grace, accept of vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in our troubles, with euerlaſting pitty, that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy may follow; That I (through this hope) may with patience ouercome all miſfortunes, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Lamen. 3.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>It is a precious thing for a man, that he carry the yoke in his youth.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>MAny a one doth GOD lay his croſſe and yoke vpon, betimes in his young bloud and youth.</p>
                        <pb n="171" facs="tcp:15111:89"/>
                        <p>Although our fleſh and bloud doe ſhrinke for it, and would gladly forbeare it, yet ſhould wee know, that it is a coſtly thing for a man, that hée be exerciſed from his youth vnder the Lords yoake, and bée rocked with the deare Croſſe, for thereby teacheth hée, not onely to eſtéeme much of Gods help, but alſo to thanke God from his heart: for his gratious care hath kept him thereby from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny terrible ſinnes (which the Aduerſarie in his youth did trouble him with.) And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is from his youth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Croſſe, therefore is hee patient, for hée knoweth well, that he ſhall find no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life heere. Therefore hath
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15111:90"/>hee is minde and longing to another world, and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to pray vnto GOD, for the gracious co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ing of his kingdome.</p>
                        <p>For ſuch and the like cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, will GOD preſerue vs alwaies vnder his yoke.</p>
                        <p>For when one croſſe is ſcant paſt, there cometh ſoone another. And heere muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> tell an example of a Chriſtian Paſtor and Preacher, which ſoone after the beginning of the Goſpel, did preach in the precinct of <hi>Weida.</hi> This ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and godly man (without doubt) loued the Lord GOD and his holy Word entirely, therefore was the Diuell his ſore enemy. And GOD the Lord (through many afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:15111:90"/>did trie his faith.</p>
                        <p>For firſt, not onely hée, but his whole houſhold, wife, and children were taken with a long laſting ſickeneſſe of the French diſeaſe, on which his wiſe and children died. Not long after, the horrible plague of Peſtilence fell vpon him: in the time of which ſickneg, the wilde-fire kindled in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e of his armes, that hee was forced to haue the ſame ſawed off: and was after wards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of his ſenſes, that hée was kept in chaines. Vpon whom the Lord ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo gracious and merciful, that he gat his ſenſes againe But ſhortly after, when hee ſound himſelfe very ill and weake, hee called on his deare
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:15111:91"/>God, with theſe and ſuch like words.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O Deare God, I thanke thee for thy gracious helpe, and euerlaſting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which thou haſt ſhewed to mee poore ſinner, through thy deare Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and let ſo happen vnto me, that thou mighteſt preſerue mee in the ſame thy euerlaſting grace and mercie. Oh, how many tribulations and ſickneſſes haſt thou layd die vpon me from my youth, haſt viſited me with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French diſeaſe &amp; Peſtilence, haſt let my wife &amp; children die, ſent the wilde fire into my arme, to bee bereaued of my wits
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:15111:91"/>and memorie, and haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee the ſame againe: O my deare GOD, what wilt thou doe more with me, and what is thy pretence?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Euen at that houre, as he thanked his deare GOD for his euerlaſting helpe, that hee had ſo heartily accepted of his Soule, and yeelded him further to GODS will and pleaſure, without doubt for diſſoluing of this life, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> with his heart, the falling ſickneſſe tooke him, by the meanes whereof hee departed out of this life, but was perfectly heard.</p>
                        <p>As God now dealt with this Chriſtian, in ſending
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:15111:92"/>him one ſorrow after an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Firſt, on his wife; then ſhortly after vpon his children, and his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, &amp;c. So will hee often times do with his Chriſtians in this life, from their youth, and it ſhall ſtand vs in good ſtead. For, nothing can bee dannable to them which bée in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                        <p>This ſame is ſomewhat a horror for our ſenſes to hear: but a Chriſtian ſhould yéeld himſelfe with patience vnto Gods will and pleaſure, as this Chriſtian man did. For like as the Lords yoake is a very coſtly thing; ſo againe is it alſo a coſtly thing to beare the ſame with patience, and tarry for his helpe.</p>
                        <pb n="177" facs="tcp:15111:92"/>
                        <p>Therefore, whoſoeuer is ſubiect vnder the Lords yoke and croſſe, let him here learne with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> to comfort himſelfe, and to pray thus:</p>
                        <p>O deare God, behold how I am heere in ſubiection vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy yoke, with many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and troubles. I know (if it bée thy will) that thy right hand can turne away all. But if it bée not thy godly pleaſure to helpe mee bodily (as thou knoweſt what is beſt) then giue mée the comfort of thy holie Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
                        <p>I reioyce, and am glad of thy goodneſſe, that thou haſt reſpect of my miſerie, and knoweſt my ſoule in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:15111:93"/>
                           <hi>Pſalme 31.</hi> I hope vpon thee, for thou art mercifull.</p>
                        <p>My heart reioyceth, that thou ſo willingly helpeſt.</p>
                        <p>Therefore (O deare God) although thou kill mee, and let mée die vnder thy yoake and croſſe, yet will I not doubt nor deſpaire of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting helpe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the fleſh is weake, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient. O deare Lord, burne, hew, ſtrike, and plague mée how thou wilt; I onely pray thee for patience and méeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="assault">
                     <pb n="179" facs="tcp:15111:93"/>
                     <head>III. Wherefore God layeth the Croſſe vpon vs.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Eſay 48.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>Behold, I wil cleanſe thee, but not as ſiluer, but I will make thee ſelected in the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of Affliction, for my ſake will I doe it.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>WE poore Creatures haue often gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from God, and forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him. Therefore it is néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that he do caſt vs into the melting Quen, like vncleane and falſified ſiluer, to bée clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and purified, to the end hée may againe haue a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight in vs: And ſo wée, deliuered from ſinne,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:15111:94"/>and comne againe into the feare of God, may kéepe his word.</p>
                     <p>This is (for all that) no euill thing, but the chiefeſt pretence and meanes, that God ſpareth thy Soule, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a while thy body, thy goods, wife, and children, &amp;c. Therewith hee thruſteth thée into the furnace of affliction, that thou maieſt thereby learn to acknowledge thy ſinnes, to be ſorry for them, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelfe before GOD, and pray for Gods grace, &amp;c. whereas otherwiſe (if thou diddeſt not ſticke in this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace) thou wouldeſt alwaies goe forward in ſin, and more and more fall into damnation.</p>
                     <p>But now, whilſt thou doſt
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:15111:94"/>conuert, God hath a liking to thee, and taketh thée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to his mercie, for his Names ſake, that is, onely therefore, that he will through Chriſt bee mercifull vnto vs, to the end wee acknowledge his Name and Mercie, and praiſe the ſame.</p>
                     <div type="section">
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>1 Cor. 11.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>When we are iudged, then ſhall wee bee chaſtiſed of the Lord, that we be not damned with the world.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>HEere doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhew the cauſe why God doth lay the croſſe vpon his people.</p>
                        <p>Hée doth the ſame, that wée may attaine vnto his holines.
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:15111:95"/>For it is certaine, if GOD ſhould giue to vs all that wee would willingly haue, wee ſhould bée ſafe, and haue no regard of our ſinnes, neither thinke on the Word or Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
                        <p>But when all goeth ouer and ouer, and now one affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and then another hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, then hath a man cauſe to haſten, not onely to prayer, but alſo to thinke, how wee with our ſinnes haue well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſuch correction: And therefore hencefoorth to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for amendement of our liues: As it is ſaide in the Epiſtle to the Hebrews: <hi>Our Father in Heauen doth cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe vs for our good, that
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:15111:95"/>we may attayne vnto his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Deare and heauenlie Father, who of thy well meaning and loue, to keepe mée vnder thy childely obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance for obtayning of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and to make mée ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, haſt laide ſo manifold corrections vpon mee: Take pitty on my Soule, and come to help me in theſe mine affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, occurrences, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the raging Diuell.</p>
                        <p>Deliuer my ſoule in this great néede from the helliſh dogges, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <pb n="184" facs="tcp:15111:96"/>
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Lament. of Ieremy 3.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>It is a coſtly thing to bée patient, and to tarry for the Lords helpe.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>MAny men do often fall vnder the croſſe, into Impatience, and Deſpaire, for they know not yet what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good God meaneth towards vs with the Croſſe: and this impatience is a great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Diuell, by which the vnfaithfull are brought, either to ſeeke meanes that bee forbidden, or through deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire (when a had conſcience meeteth with it) doe run their owne heart out, doe poyſon, drowne, hang, or kill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp;c. for they haue no
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:15111:96"/>comfort in their hearts. It fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with them, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micheas</hi> in the <hi>7.</hi> Chap. ſaith, <hi>When the day of thy Preacher commeth, they ſhall not know what to do.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Againſt ſuch afflictions doth <hi>Ieremy</hi> héere ſtrengthen vs: <hi>O</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>what a terrible &amp; woful thing it is, when a man will not acknowledge, what a louing heart God hath to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him?</hi> He begins to bee impatient, murmureth againſt God, and deſpaireth: againſt which, if any doe thinke thus in his heart, <hi>I know I haue a mercifull God in heauen, who eſteemeth of mee, as of other his deare children; and will through theſe my afflictions, ſickneſſe,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:15111:97"/>woes, and miſeries, &amp;c. put mee in minde of my ſinnes, and admoniſh mee to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that I may bee more godly, and ſhall keepe mee from ſinne:</hi> Theſe are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and happy thoughts, for they are the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt, and worthy to bée praiſed.</p>
                        <p>For whoſoeuer hath ſuch thoughts in his heart, is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient vnder the Croſſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth helpe by GOD with prayer, and hopeth for the Lords gracious houre of helpe, and is of ſure hope that it will come; if not corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet the Lord will perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare him: Therefore tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth hée for his helpe with patience.</p>
                        <pb n="187" facs="tcp:15111:97"/>
                        <p>So did the Prophet <hi>Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuk</hi> comfort in the <hi>2.</hi> Chap. <hi>The promiſe ſhall bee yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in due ſeaſon, and laſtly come to light, and not tarry away. Though it linger, tarry you: it will ſurely come, and not ſtay.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Heauenly Father, giue mee thy holy Spirit to ſtrengthen mee, that I may beare thy will with patience, that both in good and euill, I may alwaies breake my will, offer and mortifie my ſelfe, and not murmure againſt thee, although I thinke it goeth otherwiſe with mee, then I gladly would; I
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:15111:98"/>would rather that it went al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies after my will, that I might bee without Croſſes: but O Lord, doe thou thy will vpon mée, and giue mee obedience and patience in all Croſſes and Afflictions, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="assault">
                     <head>IIII. God will alſo deliuer from the Croſſe.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>1 Cor. 10.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>GOd is truſty, who will not let you bee tempted aboue your abilitie, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the temptation to get an end, that you may beare it,</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <pb n="189" facs="tcp:15111:98"/>
                     <p>HEere doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> encounter with two great afflictions which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder our faith, eſpecially when wee grone &amp; lie bedred: The firſt, that wee thinke the Croſſe to bée heauy, and too great, and feare wee muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it goe to the ground: The ſecond, that wee ſée no way nor meanes whereby wee may bee holpen; then wée make account we are vndon, and begin to doubt and to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. Therefore doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> heere comfort vs: Why ſhould you ſo deſpaire vnder the croſſe? you haue yet a true mercifull God, which laieth vpon no man more then his ability, yea, hee himſelfe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:15111:99"/>ſtrength and power to them which bee not able, and maketh the affliction a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious meanes and end, that how heauie ſoeuer the ſame ſeemeth, yet thoſe which are his, doe goe through with it, and beare it: for the croſſe is to a Chriſtian but a ſlight burthen, and a light yoake, <hi>Math. 11.</hi> vnder which the Lord himſelfe did put his godly arme, necke and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and will comfort them, as hee promiſeth, <hi>Eſay 51. I, euen I am your Comforter, &amp;c.</hi> And how long or endleſs the croſſe ſéemeth to our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, yet ſhall there be a happy end, and but a ſmall thing, as the Lord himſelfe reckoned his ſuffering, that
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:15111:99"/>it was but little, <hi>Iohn 16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So alſo the Lord GOD comforted his Chriſtians: <hi>Yet a little while, then ſhall my anger for thy ſinnes, and my diſpleaſure haue an end, Eſay 10.</hi> Heere doth the Lord giue a fine compariſon, <hi>Iohn 16.</hi> of a Woman in Child-bed, with whom it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth alſo, as if the Croſſe were importable, both Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Childe muſt goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The poore woman can doe no more, but yeeldeth her ſelfe in ſuch ſmart and deadly paine, vnto Gods will and pleaſure, and ſaith: <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I liue or die, I am the Lords.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now when the paine is at the greateſt, and no power
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:15111:100"/>more to beare: behold, it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth then after the common prouerbe, <hi>Where mans helpe endeth, there Gods helpe beginneth,</hi> It is but for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, and then in ſtead of death, two liues are brought into the world, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thinketh no more on the paine, for great ioy that ſhée hath brought a merry birth into the world. Likewiſe ſhould wée alſo comfort our ſelues, that it is but a while, then ſhall Gods helpe bee vnto vs; and in ſtead of ſorrow, ioy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſhall bee found.</p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="193" facs="tcp:15111:100"/>
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Thou moſt true and good Lord GOD and Father, giue mée, for thy Son Ieſus Chriſts ſake, through thy holy Spirit, a ſtrong truſt in thee, that I may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelf, and goe thorow with all the afflictions of the Croſſe; and ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue (although the Croſſe, to my thinking, and to all mens reaſon, ſéemeth too heauie and importable, and withall endleſſe) that it preſſe mée not downe, but bée vnto mée a light burthen, and a light yoke. And lend mée likewiſe ſtrength and able<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in putting-to thy holy
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:15111:101"/>arme and help to beare, it till I (through thy godly help) ſhall with patience ouercome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame; and that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſend to mee a happy end, and hour of help, with grace, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Rom. 8.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>I am aſſured, that the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of this life are not worthy of the glory of God, which ſhall be ſhewed to vs.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>HEer Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle puts all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of mankinde together, what name ſoeuer they haue; All diſeaſes, plagues, ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, croſſes and paſſions, and how heauy and great ſuch
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:15111:101"/>woes and miſeries doo ſéem vnto vs; and ſaith, <hi>If all the troubles of this world were heaped together, yet were all much too ſlight to bee compared to God's glory.</hi> Why wilt thou then complain ſo much of troubles and mans miſeries? It is but a little times: and then ſhall follow to euery Chriſtian Beléeuer, an vnmeaſurable and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glory.</p>
                        <p>Héer in this life let no man think that it will bee better with him, as Chriſt himſelfe ſaith; <hi>In the world you ſhall haue troubles, &amp;c.</hi> For wée are héer in the diuels houſe: if thou hold not with the hoſt, thou ſhalt haue ſmall fauour in thy lodging. Many a one
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:15111:102"/>thinks hee will go to another place, and flée away from the miſchief: but whereſoeuer he commeth, he findes the hoſte at home. Look what great dangers the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, as in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Chapter: but, the hope of euerlaſting life, and glory to-come, caried him thorow, that with patience hee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all.</p>
                        <p>As it is true, that No eye hath ſéen, nor ear hath heard, nor euer came into the heart of man, vhat ioyes, habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and glory is prepard for Chriſtians, and ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto them:</p>
                        <p>So is it moſt certain, that they ſhall haue holy, cleare,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:15111:102"/>immortall and powerfull bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and therefore néed not feare any humane miſeries, death nor diuell. And all theſe great gifts ſhall they haue through Chriſt for euermore. All ſhall bee Gods, and haue enough. A poor ſcabbed boy or wench, a poor ſcholar, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed begger, &amp;c. which put their truſt in Chriſt, ſhall haue more, and bée more rich, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n all the Emperors and Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s in this life: for, they ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the euerlaſting glory; in which, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſhall crowne them with his vnwithered Garland of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to euerlaſting heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour; as wée vſe to ſet Garlands on for an honour. All worldly honour ſhall bée
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:15111:103"/>but childrens play to ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory: for, there ſhall the Chriſtians in glory hee like the Son of GOD himſelf; yea, Lords ouer all tyrants and perſecuters, ouer the holy Angels, who ſhall bée their ſeruants, ſhall ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and wait on them; and ſhall in ſuch honour and glory haue a merry, conſtant, and quiet conſcience: where no miſ-fortune more ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe their ioyes, their euerlaſting righteouſnes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and ſaluation. Of which glory wee all ſhould comfort our ſelues in all our afflictions: then may wee, through ſuch hope, with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ouercome the Croſſe.</p>
                        <p>So doth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:15111:103"/>vs: <hi>You ſhall reioyce in the ſaluation, who were a ſmall time in ſorrow.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>2 Cor. 4. Our ſmall and ſlight trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles cauſe to vs a far more excellent and an eternall waight of glory: for, wee look not vpon the viſible, but on the inuiſible things.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="200" facs="tcp:15111:104"/>
                        <head>A Praier.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Dear and heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I acknowledge, that I, for my ſins ſake, haue well deſerued all woes and miſeries, wherein I doo ſtick, beſides euerlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I thank thée with all my heart, that thou haſt (through Chriſt) redéem'd me from ſuch euerlaſting woes; and doo beléeue, that theſe my ſorrows and troubles are but ſmal, and that vpon the ſame, ſhall follow to me and all the faithfull, an euerlaſting, and aboue all meaſure, an excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glory.</p>
                        <p>I pray thée, that thou wilt preſerue me in this poor trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:15111:104"/>life, which is ſo full of woes and miſeries, throgh comfort of thy holy Spirit in ſure hope and patience, to thy euerlaſting honour and glory, for thy dear Son Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake, his redemption, death, power, reſurrection, life and glory, Amen.</p>
                        <q>
                           <l>Set thou thy cauſe on God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</l>
                           <l>Hee will thee help in time of need.</l>
                           <l>For, he that God doth truſt,</l>
                           <l>Speed well alwaies he must,</l>
                           <l>Help thou, Lord God, euery where;</l>
                           <l>The body heere, and the ſoule there.</l>
                        </q>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:105"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:105"/>
                  <p>A COMFORT againſt the fear and terror of Death, and the Graue;</p>
                  <p>BEING An Expoſition of Doctor MARTIN LVTHER, written a little before his end.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Parker.</hi> 1624.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15111:106"/>
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:15111:106"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Expoſition of</hi> D. MARTIN LVTHER, written a little before <hi>his end.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>IOHN 8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily, verily, I ſay vnto you, If any keep my word, he ſhall neuer ſee death.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly is this ſpoken, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and daily experience, in that we ſée one carried away, and buried!</p>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:15111:107"/>
                  <p>Yet it is true, when a man ſéeks after Gods Word with his hart, beléeues on him, and vpon the ſame ſléeps or dies; he ſinks and goes hence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he might ſée death, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thereof, and is for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſaued by the Word, in that hee beleeueth, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth to depart from hence. Therefore ſhould we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans not be afraid of death.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iohn 5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, He that hears my word, and beléeues on him that ſent me, ſhal haue euerlaſting life, and not come into iudgement, but ſhall paſſe through death into life.</p>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:15111:107"/>
                  <p>THis may be called an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent comfort, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with a ſolemne Oath, That wee Chriſtians, when wee onely beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, and that the Father ſent him for our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; then néed we take no care for dying, nor bée afraid of damnation, but doo paſſe through this temporall death to euerlaſting life: that is, ſo ſoone as we are dead before all mens eyes, wée are, in the twinkling of an eye, with God in euerlaſting life. Who would then feare to die? O vnbeliefe, O originall ſinne, that thou ſhouldeſt ſo hardly beléeue ſo many Promiſes, ſo many Miracles, and ſuch
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:15111:108"/>ſolemne Oaths of the true Son of God, made vnto the Saints and children of Chriſt.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iohn 11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>I am the Reſurrection and life. He that beléeueth on me, ſhall liue, although hee die: and who liueth and beléeueth on me, ſhall not die for euer.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>IN this Saying, the Lord teacheth vs for what cauſe death is no death to vs, but a beginning of eternall life: for, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt liueth, and is the Reſurrection and the life, becauſe we are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts Body, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated to him in holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:15111:108"/>
                  <p>Therefore ſhall wee liue with him for euer, as ſure as he our head liueth; onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our life is hidden with Chriſt in GOD. <hi>But when Chriſt our life ſhall appeare, then ſhall wee alſo appeare with him in glory, Coloſ. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Lord, ſtrengthen my faith.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Theſ. 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For if we belieue, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is dead, and riſen, ſo ſhall they which do ſléep in Ieſus Chriſt, be carried away with him, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Cor. 11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Behold, I tell you a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: we ſhall not all ſléep.</p>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:15111:109"/>
                  <p>THE Holy Ghoſt hath a ſtrange ſpéech; who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that a Sléep, which the world nameth Dying; and the dead, ſléeping.</p>
                  <p>With theſe words doth the holy Ghoſt declare vnto vs in a familiar compariſon, that the death of Chriſtians is no death, but a life; and deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth to vs the temporal death of the faithfull Chriſtians, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the friendlieſt manner.</p>
                  <p>For, euen as there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing tearer or pleaſanter to a ſicke body vpon the earth, than a ſwéet ſléep, when hee ſtretches himſelf in his body, and tumbles himſelf certaine
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:15111:109"/>times to and fro vpon his bed, and feeleth grief, as if a mans head did ake. But before he bée aware, a ſoft ſléep falleth vpon him: there ſléepeth hée, and knowes not how or when. Hee heareth nothing, nor knoweth hee any thing: hée ſleepeth away both thundring and lightning; neither can he tell how long hee hath ſlept. When he awaketh, his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe and ſicknes is gone, and hee is as if hee were new borne: which euery one hath tried oftentimes in his ſléep. So, ſaith the Lord God, is it alſo with the death of euery Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>When wee haue wrought our ſelues weary vpon earth, and haue ſuffered and liued,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:15111:110"/>and often-times toſſed our ſelues to and fro vpon our groning bedde, by reaſon of our bodily ſicknes (for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt alſo, for their ſinnefull fleſh ſake, haue their bodily ſickeneſſe and griefe); then when, in the laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the ſinfull fleſh and blood is killed, and the heart hath yéelded it ſelfe priſoner, that wee may bee ſpunne new and holy (which is not done without griefe), a ſwéet ſléep commeth vpon vs, where all griefes and afflictions doo ceaſe. There a Chriſtian doth not knowe how he fell aſléep: he is not aware of any death, nor knoweth hée of any, but liueth in the Lord GOD. And in this ſléepe ſhall wée
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:15111:110"/>ſléep out all ſinne, defects, miſeries, ſickneſſe, woes and neceſſities, and ſhall awake at the laſt Day, and riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in a new, holy, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, immortall, effectuall, and clarified body, and ſhall behold GOD and his glory face to face, and whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome in euerlaſting ioy. And although one haue ſlept fiue thouſand yéeres vnder the ground, it ſhall bée as if he had ſlept but one houre; as the Chriſtians in olde time were wont to deſcribe vnto children, and to the ſimple, with example of the <hi>7</hi> Slée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. With theſe words ſhould we comfort our ſelues againſt the feare and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death: whereas wée
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:15111:111"/>alſo beléeue, and with <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> do ſing with peace &amp; ioy, I hence depart: in Gods wil my heart is comforted, béeing quiet and ſtill; as God hath ſaid, Death is my ſleep, I am not afraid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Mercifull God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I pray thée, throgh the death and reſurrection of thy Son, when I haue liued and groned mee weary, and that mine houre is comne; grant mee, O Lord, a ſweet ſleep, and take my ſoule into thy hands, Amen.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Dan. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Many which haue ſlept
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:15111:111"/>vnder the ground, ſhal awake: ſome to euerlaſting life, ſome to euerlaſting reproofe and ſhame.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>THe Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth heer to ſpeake after an Euangelicall manner, and calleth death alſo a ſléepe. As Chriſt ſpeaketh of the illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Schoole maiſters daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>The Mayden is not dead, but ſleepeth:</hi> And nameth Death, a ſléepe. And without doubt the Holy Ghoſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect heere to the death and Reſurrection of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by whom all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is taken away from death, <hi>Eſay 25.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore ſhould wée
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:15111:112"/>Chriſtians remember ſuch friendly, kind, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeeches; That wee ſpeak not ieſtingly of the death of them that ſleepe, as the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and rude people do: <hi>He is gone into the old World: Hee is gone into the old Market: Hee is at Trores: His ſpoone is fallen downe:</hi> No, it is called, fallen aſléep. S. <hi>Paul</hi> nameth it a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to bée diſſolued; Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> to put off his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, &amp;c. But in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſuch ſléepe is, can wee not perceiue or vnderſtand, more then of temporall ſléepe know wee perfectly: As for example, In the mothers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the mother knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing till it ſtirre: So we in
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:15111:112"/>bodily ſléepe can do nothing; what can wee know of the ſleepe of the Holy Ghoſt? But Chriſt inſtrueteth vs that beléeue, of ſuch ſleepe, <hi>Luke 20. They liue in God,</hi> ſaith hee.</p>
                  <p>And heere it is to bée noted, that not onely Chriſtians haue their ſleepe, but the wicked alſo: but it is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſleepe, a ſoft and ſwéete ſleepe, againſt an vnquiet and heauy ſleepe. As when one is ſicke, hee hardly ſléepeth: but he which is in health ſléepeth ſoundly. But the vngodly do dreame alwaies of the diuell, as the Rich-man. <hi>Eſay 66. Vermis eorum non morietur:</hi> But the Chriſtians do reſt in Chriſt, quietly and
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:15111:113"/>peaceable, like a little inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Chilue, which often ſlée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth ſo ſoundly (as a man ſaith) <hi>Like a vong Hare.</hi> The ſame did <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uid</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, therefore ſaith hée, <hi>Pſal. 4. I will lay mee downe and ſleepe quietly; for thou onely, O Lord, makeſt mee to dwell in ſafety.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From ſuch ſleep ſhall be alſo a waking to all them which beleeue on Chriſt, and haue holden with his holy Word and Sacraments, and they ſhall bée comforted. They ſhall riſe againe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glory, and receiue the euerlaſting garland of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Heauenly, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and immortall Crowne, and eſcape euerlaſting iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:15111:113"/>and ſhame.</p>
                  <p>But the vngodly which haue done euill, forgotten the couenant of their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and not beleeued on Chriſt, they ſhall awake to euerlaſting reproofe and ſhame.</p>
                  <p>A faire ſimilitude of hoth reſurrections haue wée, <hi>Gen. 40</hi> on <hi>loſeph,</hi> the Butler and Baker: They were all thrée laid in priſon, and came to liberty againe, which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Reſurrection. One of them was ſet free, came to honour and to his Office a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: The other was alſo quit of his troubles, but commeth to the Gallowes: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſignifieth our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who was alſo
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:15111:114"/>put into this priſon, but guiltleſſe. The Butler ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth all honeſt Chriſtians which acknowledge their ſins, and with hearty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and ſorrow, haue belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on Chriſt: they ſhall at the latter day bee placed with him in euerlaſting glory. The Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſignifieth all the vngodly: they ſhall bee alſo quit of their priſon (that is, their Graues) but to euerlaſting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Surely, ſurely, the graue is a very ſoft reſting bed for Chriſtians, which the Lord Ieſus hath before warmed for them, that they neede not bee afraide thereof: Therein haue they a good, ſoft, and quiet ſleepe. There ſhall
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:15111:114"/>they alwaies dreame of the Vine. For the Vine ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt; and the Grapes. the ſweete doctrine of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goſpell, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <hi>Mathew 7.</hi> appeareth. <hi>Doe men gather Grapes on Thornes? Iohn 15. Ego ſum vitis vera, &amp;c.</hi> There dreame the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in death and Graue, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and of his ſwée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Doctrine. And in ſuch ſoft dreames reſt they ſo ſoft, that they thinke many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares bee as though they had ſcantly ſlept an houre.</p>
                  <p>But the Baker (that is the vngodly) dreameth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies of the Diuell, and how the birds doe eate his
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:15111:115"/>Bread out of the Baſket. The Birds are the Diuels, which eate away Gods word from him: Such eating and gnawing muſt they féele for euer; whereof wee haue a ſimilitude, which our El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders fained of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> that the Eagle did eate out his heart, and the heart did grow within him againe, and the eating neuer had end. The ſame doe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked féele truely, as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tragedy of the Rich man ſheweth.</p>
                  <p>That there are two reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, whereby all men may direct themſelues, God cauſeth to bee preached vnto vs in the time of Grace: Therefore, whoſoeuer will
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:15111:115"/>eſcape ſuch euerlaſting gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eating conſciences, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh paine and torment, let him take hold of the ſweete doctrine of the Holy Goſpell, and in the Sacraments, put therewith comfort into his heart, truſt, and beléeue, as Gods word doth plentifully ſhew him; for ſo it muſt bée, as Chriſt very comfortably promiſeth, <hi>Mark 16. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleeueth, and is bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſhall be ſaued, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="226" facs="tcp:15111:116"/>
                     <head>A Prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Euerlaſting God and Father, which art not a God of the dead, but of the liuing: For in thée doe all they liue, which reſt vnder the Earth in their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:</p>
                     <p>Wee pray thy fatherly goodneſſe, that thou wilt not let the thinking of death, or of his ſting, bee a feare vnto vs; but wilt through grace of thy holy Spirit, keepe vs in ſhe right faith of thy déere Sonne, who is the truth and life, and giue vs a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that wee may liue Chriſtianly, and depart hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily out of this vale of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:15111:116"/>ſleepe in peace and ioy' and reſt quietly, vntill thou open our Graues; And tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the ſound of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, bée waked againe to life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1. Cor. 15.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>It is ſowed a naturall body, &amp;c.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>HEere the Holy Ghoſt vſeth another word, and calleth Dying, To be ſowed, which is a friendly ſimilitude: wee are the Wheatcornes (as Chriſt himſelfe ſaith. <hi>Ioh. 12</hi>) Now is the ſéed which the Huſbandman ſoweth
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:15111:117"/>glory, and bring foorth much fruit, whereon God the holie Trinitie ſhall haue euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioy and pleaſure. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould wee not bée afraide of death.</p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, come and ſowe vs and our Children in thy Churchyard, that wee neuer neede to bee afraide for any trouble, néede, warres, or hearts ſorrow, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="229" facs="tcp:15111:117"/>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Luke 2.</bibl>
                        <p>The old man <hi>Simeon</hi> ſingeth.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>Lord, now letteſt thou thy Seruant depart in peace.</p>
                     <p>THis olde Chriſtian <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> calleth Death, a Departing in Peace, which is alſo the ſaying of the Holie Ghoſt: for there is nothing in our whole body vpon earth, but vnreſtfulneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe, one after another.</p>
                     <p>But when we, our Lord and GOD, ſhall goe out of this vale of miſerie, and come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our euerlaſting Countrey, then come wee vnto Peace. What man would not then
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:15111:118"/>once haue alſo ſuch peace and reſt?</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Philip 1.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I deſire to depart, or to bée diſſolued, and to bee with Chriſt; which is alſo much better.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>HEere Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth Death, A Diſſoluing or a departure: for héere we are bound to ſinnefull fleſh, to paines and labour, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſooner bee quit thereof, then through the happie houre.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2. Pet. 1.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I know that I ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put off my Tabernacle.</p>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="231" facs="tcp:15111:118"/>
                     <p>SAint <hi>Peter</hi> nameth Death héere, the Going out of a poore, ruinated, ſinfull, and wofull Habitation, and to be remooued into a glorious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, or to put off an olde worne gowne, and to put on an immortall and heauenly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, whereof we ought by good reaſon to reioyce.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Eſay 26.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Go hence (my people) into a chamber, and ſhut the doore after thée: hide thée awhile, till the indignation bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt.</p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Eſay 57.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The righteous are plue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked away from their misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune;
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:15111:119"/>and they which haue wandred righteouſly, do come into peace, and reſt in their chambers.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>HOW friendly and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpeaketh the Holie Ghoſt of the death of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and giueth the ſame fiue beautifull names!</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Dying, hee calleth, Going into a Chamber, to goe into a pleaſant Parlour, as often-times a man buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a pleaſant roome for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, where hee would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly héee alone, and bee quiet from his children and houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, he nameth death, Hiding one a while, till Gods wrath and puniſhment bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſt,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:15111:119"/>as when one ſtands vnderneath for ſoule weather, or hideth his daughter, when an army paſſes thorow, ſo doth the Lord God lay vs vp, that no miſfortune hurt vs.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Death is called, Plucking away from miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: for when GOD will puniſh the World for their ſinnes, hee taketh firſt his Chriſtians away, gathereth them together, remooueth them into a place of ſafetie, that they be not hurt.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, it is called De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting in peace, as <hi>Simeon</hi> did.</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, Reſting in their chambers: for elſe vpon earth will be ſmall reſt or peace.</p>
                     <pb n="234" facs="tcp:15111:120"/>
                     <p>But the Graue of the Chriſtians hee calleth, our Chambers and reſting beds, wherein no man ſhall diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et vs, or awake vs, nor any man can driue vs out,</p>
                     <p>There would many a one alſo haue gladly a reſting Chamber vpon Earth, and buildeth often with great charges in quiet places, euen where hee heareth no knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or running, eſpecially when hee is ſick; but all is to no effect, for on Earth is no ſuch fléeping Chamber to bée had: wee are awaked with care, ſorrow, need, world, and Diuell.</p>
                     <p>So are our Chambers vpon earth but hired Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: although wee haue
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:15111:120"/>bought them, wee know not when wee ſhall goe foorth of them. But the Chambers in the Church-yard are quiet, and our owne. There ſhall no care, ſickeneſſe, nor Diuell, make vs vnquiet, neyther ſhall anie man driue vs out, till the Lord Ieſus awake vs to euerlaſting life.</p>
                     <p>This is comfortably and ioyfully ſpoken of the death of Chriſtians, and of the Graue: Hee that beléeueth it, will béeglad from his heart for the houre.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Philip. 1.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Chriſt is my life, and Death is my gaines.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>SAint <hi>Paul</hi> giueth Death heere, a fayre name, his
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:15111:121"/>greateſt and beſt gaines: for there hee layeth in exchange a mortall, needefull, defectiue, ſinnefull, weake, ſicke, and vnperfect body, and taketh for the ſame againe, for vſurie and gaines, an euerlaſting, immortall, holy, ſtrong, and ſpirituall body, which may be called a Gaines: who would be afraid to die?</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 116.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The death of his Saints is precious in the ſight of the Lord.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>BEfore the world and our fiue Senſes, nothing is more horrible nor terrible yea, nor more diſhonourable, then death, and a dead body.</p>
                     <pb n="237" facs="tcp:15111:121"/>
                     <p>But before the face of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, the Death of Chriſtians is the faireſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Gen. 15.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>God ſaith to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Thou ſhalt goe to thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with peace.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>HEere God himſelfe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Death, a Going home into his Country, and to come to his Parents and Friends; And withall, vpon the iourney, to be conducted with peace.</p>
                     <p>As a childe that hath beene long amongſt ſtrangers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth in his heart, that hee may once goe home, ſo ſhould wee alſo reioyce, when our
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:15111:122"/>deaths houre approacheth, that wee may goe home into our euerlaſting Country, and with all Chriſtendome, haue an euerlaſting Nuptiall day and ioy.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Geneſ. 25.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Abraham</hi> was gathered to his people.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>SO doth the Holy-Ghoſt ſpeak of <hi>Abrahams</hi> death: For heer on earth wee are among a ſort of euill degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated people, with whom wée ſhall bée plagued and marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; as the Children of <hi>If<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> were of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and of their Taſke-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
                     <p>This Sentence of holie
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:15111:122"/>Scripture, ſhould wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and keepe: wherewith wee may in dangerous times learne to prepare vs, and to comfort our ſelues, and pray with our hearts for an happy houre.</p>
                     <p>And when we ſée death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, or thinke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, not to be afraid.</p>
                     <p>Vpon theſe ſentences out of holy Scripture, haue the honeſt Chriſtians alwaies had goodly wordes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue comforted themſelues againſt Death: Of which wee will rehearſe ſome.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cicely,</hi> a godly Chriſtian woman of <hi>Rome,</hi> when her kindred would perſwade her ſhe ſhould deny our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:15111:123"/>Chriſt, and what ſhee did meane to make ſuch light ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her body and life, the higheſt treaſure and beſt pawn we haue? Shee anſwered, If it had concerned onely our life, wee ſhould not willingly loſe it. But I beléeue another bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, which laſteth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, of which IESUS CHRIST hath preached vnto vs.</p>
                     <p>This true Martyr and Confeſſor of the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith, did take holde on the right comfort. Shee was not afraid of the horrible Death: for, ſhee knew, that this temporall Death was a beginning of euerlaſting life.</p>
                     <p>Item, whereas wee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:15111:123"/>doo ſay and confeſſe, <hi>Miſeria hominis moritur, non homo:</hi> that is, Of a Chriſtian dieth nothing but his warres and miſeries: hee dieth not. And it is true. No ioyfuller houre can happen vnto vs Chriſtians vpon earth, than the happy houre of death: for euen in the twinkling of an eye, all our woes and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="242" facs="tcp:15111:124"/>inceſſantly, deaths ſting and ſickneſſe: but when wee are dead in the ſight of the world, then doo wée firſt liue, and doo neuer feél any more either danger or death. For, our temporall death is an end of death, and a beginning of life.</p>
                     <p>Item, whereas the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſaith, Without the knowledge of Chriſt, death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſinne: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="243" facs="tcp:15111:124"/>ledgeth Chriſt, to him is temporall death the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for ſinne; whereby fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſin is ſcoured quite out of our fleſh and bloud, body and ſoule, that we neuer ſinne more.</p>
                     <p>Therefore wée ſhould (by good reaſon) be glad of death, that wée may bée once rid of that ſhamefull ſinne, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee are plagued and tormented day and night: as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cryeth out ouer this proſecuting ſinne, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans 7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, as honeſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue out of Gods Word, for their comfort, ſpoken friendly and familiarly of death: ſo haue they alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen comfortable names to
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:15111:125"/>the Graues, and to Burials.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prudentius</hi> dooth call the Graue, Our Lord God's Iewell-houſe; wherein hée hath his deare Gold and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and halloweth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and Bones of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and will at the laſt Day demand them again by waight.</p>
                     <p>The holy Scripture na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Buriall-place, A Houſe of the Liuing, who dwell there aliue indeed. All other dwellings vpon earth (although they bee built of pure Cypreſſe and Marble) are but Peſt-houſes, where men doo ſicken and die. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Graues of Chriſtians are the Houſes of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
                     <pb n="245" facs="tcp:15111:125"/>
                     <p>The Latine Church calls the Church-yard, A ſléeping houſe. The Dutchmen call it God's Field, wherein God ſoweth vs, as hath béen ſaid before.</p>
                     <p>Beſides all theſe, Chriſt our Lord was buried: hee hath hallowed and warmed the graue for vs, and left his linnen clothes therein. And the holy Angels dwell in the graue, doo watch and kéep vs in our reſting bed.</p>
                     <p>Now, he that is ſo inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Gods Word, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth, deſireth from his hart to bee out of his groning bed of ſorrow, and to bee in his reſting bed.</p>
                     <p>Whereupon, the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt help vs, through
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:15111:126"/>grace of thy holy Spirit, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom. 14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Whether I liue or die, I am the Lords.</p>
                     </q>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, all they which are baptized in thee, are baptized in thy death. I am baptized in thée, therefore am I alſo baptized in thy death. I will with thy help die merrily and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; hoping, that as I haue bin partaker of thy troubles, I ſhall be alſo partaker of thy glory.</p>
                        <p>O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:15111:126"/>haſt prayed vpon the Croſſe, <hi>Father, forgiue them:</hi> So, Lord, doo I forgiue all that haue done againſt mee, that thou maiſt pardon mee of all my ſinnes.</p>
                        <p>O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou haſt called vpon the Croſſe, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi> Lord, leaue mee not at the point of death.</p>
                        <p>O Lord, thou haſt ſaid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſs, <hi>Eather, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit:</hi> euen ſo, Lord, do I commend my poor ſoule into thy hands, Amen.</p>
                        <epigraph>
                           <q>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Pſalm 31.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <p>Into thy hands I commit my Spirit: thou haſt redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:15111:127"/>me, O Lord GOD of truth.</p>
                           </q>
                        </epigraph>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>An Epitaph of Gaſper Huberin.</head>
                     <p>Oh a ſinner! Born, aliue, and dead am I.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt my Lord, Renew, forgiue, and wake me vp.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I am faithfull. Preſerue, make cleare, and ſaue me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Pſalme 4.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>I laid me downe, and ſlept quietly, for thou onely (O Lord) helpeſt me, that I dwel in ſafetie.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="249" facs="tcp:15111:127"/>
                     <head>How wee in the euerlaſting life to come, ſhall ſee and knowe one another.</head>
                     <head type="sub">I beléeue a reſurrection of the fleſh, and an euerlaſting life.</head>
                     <p>WHen one preacheth of the reſurrection of the dead, and hath heard how the dead doo riſe; there ariſeth a queſtion amongſt many; If wee alſo, in the euerlaſting life to-come, ſhall knowe one another, as we doo héer? Of the Reſurrection is no doubt; thereof are wee certaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: and withall we know, that, if any haue a defect or
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:15111:128"/>want on his body, that he hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were lame, or a Cripple, and had not all his limbs, the ſame ſhall be all taken away in the reſurrection of the dead, and ſhall bee altogether whole, and haue all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers wholly. But ſhall wee in another life knowe one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other? Héerto doo the learned men giue this anſwer: Yes, wee ſhall knowe one another there. Séeing that God will make the whole man aliue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with fleſh and bones, ſhall knowledge and memory be gone? Nothing at all.</p>
                     <p>Therefore ſhall you héer learne, that wee ſhall knowe all; not onely thoſe which we now knowe, but thoſe which wée knew not, nor in our life
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:15111:128"/>time had euer ſéen, the ſame ſhall we ſee, and knowe how to call them, and they vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                     <p>The Learned alſo doo ſay, that the Chriſtians ſhall not onely knowe one another, but the vngodly alſo: and the wicked ſhall knowe them whom they haue héer oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and perſecuted, <hi>Sapience, chap. 5.</hi> There ſhall the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſay with repentance, <hi>Are not theſe they whom wee haue mocked? Oh how are they now reckoned among the children of God!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="argument">
                     <pb n="252" facs="tcp:15111:129"/>
                     <head>I. Teſtimony of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</head>
                     <p>THe firſt proof they take from <hi>Adam.</hi> You know, that God made Heauen and Earth, with all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Creatures: and <hi>Adam</hi> was made laſt of all. Then GOD let all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Beaſts paſſe by him: and when he ſaw them, he knew euery Beaſt, and his proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and gaue to euery Beaſt his name according to his property. As <hi>Adam</hi> now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, ſo muſt they bée called at this preſent day. If <hi>Adam</hi> then in the naturall body, and before the Fall, had ſuch ſharp eyes, that he could ſee the Beaſts in his heart; as for example, what the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:15111:129"/>and property of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Stork is, which hath a naturall born loue to the old ones that haue brought her vp: ſhall not we much more in the new ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall body, which ſhall beare the Image of Chriſt, bee a thouſand times wiſer, and knowe all? This is a right good argument.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="argument">
                     <head>The II. Argument.</head>
                     <p>THis is like the firſt, that <hi>Adam</hi> knew <hi>Eue</hi> ſo ſoon as God brought her to him, when hée had made her of his ribs, before GOD ſaid one word vnto him. There it is rightly ſaid, <hi>Ille eſt felix, qui potuit rerum cognoſcere
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:15111:130"/>cauſas.</hi> Therefore ſaid <hi>Adam</hi> (according vnto the Hebrew ſpeech) This is mercifulnes: ſhe ſhall haue a true hart, and ſhall bee called <hi>Woman, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whil'ſt <hi>Adam</hi> in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life had ſuch ſharp eies: ſhall wee not much more in the ſpirituall and euerlaſting life, haue much ſharper eies, that wee knowe one another, and alſo thoſe which in this life we haue not knowne? I cannot finde any thought in me, to withdraw it from mee, that it ſhould not be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="argument">
                     <head>The III. Argument.</head>
                     <p>THe third proof they take from Chriſt, when <hi>Mary
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:15111:130"/>Magdalen</hi> mette him in the garden, who (being yet in her ſinnefull body) did quickly knowe him by his ſpéech, and likewiſe the Apoſtles alſo: much more ſhall wee knowe one another, when wee ſhall haue pure clarified eies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="argument">
                     <head>The IIII. Argument.</head>
                     <p>CHriſt laieth before vs the Rich-man and poor <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> which is no ſimilitude, but a true Hiſtory acted; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bée wonderfull and ſtrange vnto vs, that in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life they ſhall both know one another.</p>
                     <p>In brief: There ſhall be a right perfect knowledge, that wée ſhall alſo knowe the
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:15111:131"/>high Maieſty of God, and ſée him face to face, as <hi>Iob</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelf, chapter <hi>19. I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Such knowledge ſhal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto vs, as the cuſtome was in old time amongſt our Elders, when they kept the hallowing of their Church, when all the friends and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red came together once in a yéer, which had in a long time before not ſéen one another, as they vſe often at Eaſter and Chriſtmaſſe to viſit their good friends. There are they knowne amongſt the kinred: Is not that my Vncle? Is not this my Aunt? Are not theſe alſo my couſins and friends? So that they knowe one another with great ioy.
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:15111:131"/>Then knowe, that at the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Day ſhall be the right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed day, that right Church Holy-day ſhall begin; where all Chriſtendome ſhall come together, make themſelues knowne one to another, and ſhall haue an euerlaſting Church-Feaſt, a perpetuall Eaſter-Feaſt, and a day of eternall ioy.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things ſhould a Chriſtian remember: for, they ſerue to this end, that many a one may bée comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith, when hée muſt depart from a good Friend, Father or Mother, Brother or Siſter, goeth far off, and knoweth not at his returne if hée ſhall finde them in health.</p>
                     <p>Or elſe in the time of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:15111:132"/>when we ſhould depart one from another, then may one comfort himſelf in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thus: I ſhall not yet loſe him altogether: I know, that our Lord God hath appointed a Church-holy-day, where my deareſt children, brethren, ſiſters and good friends, come to mee again: there will wee conſult together for euer.</p>
                     <p>The ſame is a notable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, when his father, mother, and kinred bee dead, that hée be not diſcour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ged, but know that they bee but gone before him. And therefore it is called thus:
<q>
                           <l>Coming again makes me ſure,</l>
                           <l>That I eſteem not departure.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="259" facs="tcp:15111:132"/>
                        <head>A Praier.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> LORD Ieſus Chriſt, which art the conductor of life, thou through thy death haſt ouercome euerlaſting death in victory, made ſin and death to be nothing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeſt with a double oath, that we which kéep thy word ſtedfaſtly in our hearts, ſhall not ſee death eternally; dooſt comfort and promiſe to vs thy faithfull, that we ſhall be for euer in the height of ioy and ſaluation where thou art.</p>
                        <p>Therefore wee pray thee from our hearts, O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that thou wilt, through the grace of thy holy
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:15111:133"/>Spirit preſerue vs conſtantly in ſuch faith, that thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may quickly come, that wee may bee deliuered out of this vale of miſery, that wée and our faithfull Children, Parents, Brethren and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, all our kinsfolks, and all godly people (through thy ſpirituall grace) may bee brought one to another, as thou didſt bring to the widow of <hi>Naim,</hi> her dear ſon in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily maner. That thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt alſo (as thy Word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth) graciouſly grant, that as <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency knew <hi>Eue,</hi> of whom he before did knowe nothing; and as thou, after thy holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, didſt make thy ſelf knowne, we likewiſe may ſée
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:15111:133"/>and knowe one another in the higheſt ioy of thy ſaluation, and to thy laud &amp; praiſe, may conſult together euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly. Amen, Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="262" facs="tcp:15111:134"/>
                     <head>Heer after follow godly Sayings and Prayers, taken out of the Pſalms of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to be vſed in the extreme neceſſity of death.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
                        </hi> Lord, rebuke me not in thy Indignation: neither cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten thou mee in thy heauy diſpleaſure.</p>
                     <p>Haue mercy vpon mée, O
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:15111:134"/>Lord, for I am weake: my ſoule alſo is ſore troubled, but Lord, how long?</p>
                     <p>Turne thee, O Lord, and deliuer my ſoule. O ſaue me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                     <p>O Lord my God, in thée haue I put my truſt: ſaue me from all them that perſecute me, and deliuer me.</p>
                     <p>Haue mercy vpon mee, O Lord: conſider the trouble which I ſuffer of them that hate mee, thou that lifteſt me vppe from the very gates of death.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, thou art hee that tooke mee out of my mothers womb: thou waſt my hope, when I hanged yet vpon my mothers breſts.</p>
                     <p>Go not from me then: for,
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:15111:135"/>trouble is hard at hand, and there is none to help me.</p>
                     <p>I am powred out like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: all my bones are out of ioynt: my heart in the midſt of my body, is euen like mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting waxe.</p>
                     <p>My ſtrength is dried vp like a potſhard, my tongue cleaueth to my gummes: but be not thou farre from me, O Lord, thou art my ſuccour, haſte thee to helpe me.</p>
                     <p>Tarry not long (O Lord) for I am very faint.</p>
                     <p>Quicken my ſoule (O Lord) and bring me foorth in the way of righteouſneſſe, for thy names ſake.</p>
                     <p>Vnto thee (O Lord) I lift my ſoule, my God, I truſt in thee. O let me not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:15111:135"/>leſt mine enemies triumph ouer mee. For all they that hope in thee, ſhall not be aſhamed.</p>
                     <p>Thou art the God of my ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>Call to remembrance thy tender mercies, and thy louing kindneſſes, which haue euer béene of olde.</p>
                     <p>Remember not the ſinnes and offences of my youth, but according vnto thy mercie thinke vpon mee (O Lord) for thy goodnes.</p>
                     <p>For thy Names ſake (O Lord) be mercifull vnto my ſinne, for it is great.</p>
                     <p>Turne thee vnto me, and haue mercie vpon me, for I am deſolate and oppreſſed.</p>
                     <p>The ſorrowes of my heart
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:15111:136"/>are great. O bring mee out of my troubles.</p>
                     <p>Looke vpon mine aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and miſerie, and forgiue me all my ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>O kéepe my ſoule, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer mee: let mee not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, for I haue put my truſt in thée.</p>
                     <p>The Lord is my light, and my ſaluation: whom then ſhould I feare?</p>
                     <p>The Lord is the ſtrength of my life: of whom then ſhould I bee afraid?</p>
                     <p>Though an hoaſt of men were laide againſt mee, yet ſhall not my heart bee afraide: and though there roſe vp war againſt mee, yet will I truſt in him.</p>
                     <p>O hide not thou thy face
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:15111:136"/>from mée, caſt not thy ſeruant off in diſpleaſure.</p>
                     <p>Thou art my ſuccour, leaue me not, neither forſake me, O God my Sauiour.</p>
                     <p>The Lord is my ſtrength, and my ſhield: my heart ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in him.</p>
                     <p>In thee, O Lord, is my truſt: let mee neuer bee put to confuſion.</p>
                     <p>Bowe downe thine eare to mee, make haſte to deliuer mee.</p>
                     <p>Thou art my ſtrong hold, and my caſtle. O bee thou my guide, and leade mee for thy Names ſake.</p>
                     <p>Into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Spirit: deliuer me (O Lord God of truth).</p>
                     <p>O Lord, conſider my
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:15111:137"/>trouble, and know my Soule in aduerſitie.</p>
                     <p>My hope is in thee (O Lord) thou art my God.</p>
                     <p>Shew mee the light of thy countenance, help me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                     <p>Let mee not be confounded (O Lord) for I call vpon thée.</p>
                     <p>Thou art my defence, in the trouble that is come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout mee: O compaſſe thou mee about alſo with the ioy of deliuerance.</p>
                     <p>Striue thou with them (O Lord) that ſtriue with mee, fight thou againſt them that fight againſt mee, and ſtand vp to helpe me.</p>
                     <p>Awake, Lord, and ſtand vp: auenge thou my cauſe,
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:15111:137"/>my God and my Lord.</p>
                     <p>Thou art my helper and redéemer, make no long tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, O my God.</p>
                     <p>Ariſe, O Lord, help me, and deliuer mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                     <p>Haue mercie vpon mee (O Lord) after thy goodneſſe, and according to thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies do away mine offences.</p>
                     <p>For I acknowledge my faults, and my ſinne is euer before me.</p>
                     <p>Againſt thée onely haue I ſinned, and done euill in thy ſight.</p>
                     <p>Caſt mee not away from thy preſence.</p>
                     <p>Heare my prayer, O Lord, and hide not thy ſelfe from my Petition. Take heede vnto
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:15111:138"/>mee, and heare me, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue my ſoule.</p>
                     <p>Fearefulneſſe and tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are come vpon mee, and an horrible dread hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed me.</p>
                     <p>Bee mercifull vnto me (O God) bee mercifull vnto mee, for my ſoule truſteth in thee, and vnder the ſhadow of thy wings ſhall be my refuge.</p>
                     <p>Heare my crying (O God) giue heede vnto my prayer: for thou art my hope, a ſtrong Tower for mee againſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
                     <p>Take mee out of the myre, that I ſinke not.</p>
                     <p>Heare mee (O Lord) and turne thee vnto me, according vnto thy great mercie.</p>
                     <p>I am poore, and in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:15111:138"/>haſte thée O God for to helpe mee: For thou art my helpe, my Redéemer and my God: oh make no long tarrying.</p>
                     <p>In thee (O Lord) is my truſt, let me neuer bee put to confuſion: For thou art the thing that I long for, thou art my hope euen from my youth.</p>
                     <p>Forſake mee not, O Lord, when my ſtrength fayleth mee: for mine enemies that lay white for my ſoule take their counſell together.</p>
                     <p>Go not farre from mee, O my God: my God, haſt thee to helpe mee.</p>
                     <p>O remember not mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, but haue merey vpon me, and that ſoone.</p>
                     <pb n="272" facs="tcp:15111:139"/>
                     <p>Helpe me (O Lord my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) for the glorie of thy Name: O deliuer mee, and forgiue mee my ſinnes for thy Name ſake.</p>
                     <p>Comfort the ſoule of thy ſeruant: for thou Lord art good and gracious, and of great mercie vnto all them that call vpon thee.</p>
                     <p>In the time of trouble I call vpon thee, turne to me, haue mercie vpon mee, giue thy ſtrength to thy ſeruant.</p>
                     <p>Thou (O Lord God) art full of compaſſion, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, long-ſuffering, great in goodneſſe and truth.</p>
                     <p>The ſnares of death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed mee round about, the paines of hell gat holde vpon me.</p>
                     <pb n="273" facs="tcp:15111:139"/>
                     <p>I found trouble and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe: O Lord deliuer my ſoule.</p>
                     <p>Thy mercie (O Lord) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euer: deſpiſe not the worke of thine owne hands.</p>
                     <p>Enter not into Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy ſeruant (O Lord) for in thy ſight ſhall no man liuing be iuſtified.</p>
                     <p>Bring my ſoule out of trouble, for I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="274" facs="tcp:15111:140"/>
                     <head>A Prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> My God, my Lord, and Father, now ſhew vnto my poore ſoule, that ſhe may perceiue, that thou art my ſtrong rock, caſtle, ſhield, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, defence, hope, ſuccour, refuge, defender and goodnes, that I in this great trouble for mine enemies, through thy godly grace, helpe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, may bee preſerued. Lord, in thee I put my truſt, let me not bee put to confuſion. Into thy hands I commend my ſpirit: deliuer mee, Lord God of truth, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="275" facs="tcp:15111:140"/>
                     <head>A Prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Father, receiue againe the thing which thou haſt created. O Sonne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the thing which thou haſt gouerned. O Holy Ghoſt fetch the thing which thou ſo boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully haſt preſerued. Three perſons and one verie God, I beſéech you remember not mine offences for euer. For I crie, Lord God and Father, mercie. Lord God Sonne, mercie, Lord God Holy Ghoſt mercie, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="276" facs="tcp:15111:141" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>When thou departeſt from a ſicke perſon, ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</head>
                     <p>IN your trouble and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, call vnto the Lord and crie vnto your God, and hée will heare your voice, and your crying commeth before him in his eares: And God which called you vnto his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glorie by Chriſt Ieſu, ſhall his owne ſelfe, after you haue ſuffered a little affliction, make you perfect, ſhall ſettle, ſtrength ſtabliſh and ſaue you. To him be glory and dominion for euer and euer.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15111:141"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
